yep everything should be okay now
okay so welcome guys to the next wasabi
welded research experience
this is number 23 and today we're
talking about how to get uh babisavi
coinjoin magic into other bitcoin
software wallets uh other than just
wasabi wallet i'm curious because i
think that's a very important topic to
delve down to and we'll have a couple
nice guests joining us today
um
and including mr cooks
so maybe andrew could you
quickly say hello and especially can
introduce your work at btc specifically
the plug-in system as i think that will
be valuable for the future conversation
yeah sure max uh so hi guys um so
my name is andrew um
you can call me cooks um at least on
twitter or wherever you see me
um i work
full-time on bdc pay um and
one of the latest features that we've
been working on is uh is a plug-in
system
we're kind of trying to market it as uh
the fancy term seems to be that's taking
the most is uh the wordpress of bitcoin
although that's a bit uh
less mislea
it's not misleading but it's uh it's a
big broad term
is that a compliment or an insult
i'm not sure i think it's like a
double-edged sword right so wordpress is
like everybody builds a wordpress but at
the same time wordpress kind of sucks
when you really get into it
so i'm hoping we don't end up in that
situation
um
yeah so we're trying to take it super
slow it's with how we flush it out just
trying to make sure that it comes out
right
and that we exposed just enough to you
know be able to expand
on it and not too much that you know
everything gets crazy and nothing works
anymore
um
so
one so we are we we kind of already have
uh there's two kind of plugins in ptcp
actually three if you really want to
look at it that way
one of them is
um the docker plug-ins that we kind of
tell people to just integrate their
services in there
that's basically like people adding
electrum server to their
to their btc install
then you've got the integration so
plugins like wordpress
integrations that's just completely
external of btc pay it's just something
that you have to code for specific
platforms like on wordpress so that's
php
um other stuff and then there's the new
version the new kind of plugins which is
uh c-sharp plugins directly inside the
p2c pay code code base
um where basically we expose a few
interfaces and then people implement
them
and they upload the dlls and we load
these contracts inside btc pay and they
can extend the ui
they can run background services and all
sorts of crazy stuff
i don't know if that's a good enough
intro i could probably dive uh do a
deeper dive but
yeah i'm maybe a bit curious on how deep
the plug-in system will go like how far
can we manipulate ptcpa as a plug-in
developer
so
okay so
one thing we're trying to do is
make it pretty extensive
so
right now it's quite basic in that
we expose a few interfaces which is uh
one of them is like a ui extension
interface where
we have these little pieces of uh
markers across the ui
and you as a plug-in developer can just
say oh i want to place this
this uh html
uh partial view
in this part of the ui and then you can
just add stuff to it so one
one usage of that is basically just
putting like an extra navigation item
in the side menu or the top navigation
and that links to pages that you create
yourself in your in your plugin so you
can extend
uh the current ui and then you can add
new pages new routes um all sorts of
stuff like that
um one thing we're doing with that
is basically
let's see what is there um i've been
working on
just a small
like demo but uh with the liquids uh
integration so
the first thing i did was basically
allow a way to add uh liquid acid so
that they can just
so that you don't have to hard code
liquid assets inside btta like they're
like it is currently right now you have
to do a pull request to the main code
base
you set the asset id and all that stuff
in the code base and
we merge it and then you have to wait
for a release
with the liquid plug-in
you'll be able to
um just have a ui that's defined in the
in the plug-in
and
on startup on the application startup it
will just load the
the assets you saved in there
um so that's one thing so that basically
adds
uh configuration
uh background services
at startup
and also ui
your ui
additional ui and
extending the current ui and that it
shows like a new navigation item in the
server
uh so it can get pretty excessive you
can build quite a lot so that's one of
the first demo plugins we're also
trying to move existing features
into into plugins so that the code base
becomes a bit more lean
since we've been building a lot of stuff
over the years and
at some point you have to say okay maybe
maybe we took this too far with features
that
we should try and you know be a bit more
gentle with what goes in there
by default
uh so one thing we're looking at is
basically one thing i've been playing
with is um moving the shopify
integration into a plug-in
and making that section of the ui also
extendable so that people can build
their own
uh deeper integrations with other
platforms in a similar way
i already have a few of those planned
out
um
what else is there
but so for example there's no hindrance
in having a plugin that for example
signs bitcoin transactions in a custom
way
um
it all depends on how much we expose in
the
in the interfaces i mean you can build
an entire wallet interface if you wanted
to
so that you you could do do it exactly
the way you wanted to
because right now the wallet send page
in btc pay is you know it's like defined
as this there's no extension points in
that there's no way to
modify the flow and that's in a in a
specific way at least
maybe in the future would be possible
but uh one way to get around that if you
have a very specific flow such as use an
external
um
an external wallet flow would be to
either build an entire ui and just
either
you could probably like replace the
wallet send link with
with the new one and
make that show and said so there is no
there is no hard limit um the only limit
that there is is
making sure that the current code base
is extendable to to the means that you
want it to be
and i mean we're we're not really saying
that we're going to have
um
main
uh main blockages in terms of what you
want want to extend we'll we'll see you
as time goes if there's feedback to add
another an extra thing in a specific
section in the uh in the ui will
probably do it
um yeah
it's still very early it's what i'm
saying so
we can we can really just uh play around
and see what
what would work best in a way that's
flexible for everyone
yeah that's super fascinating uh so
thanks for the ui explanations um and it
seems quite nice
but one other use case that i think is
more of a background feature kind of
that as soon as points are received uh
the wasabi demon in the plug-in kind of
starts coinjoining it directly
is that kind of more advanced demon
functionality
doable via plugin
um okay so that depends in in how
you want to integrate would you so
there's two things to it you can either
do it as a background service inside btc
peso um
we would you would we have a dependency
injection container that's just a dot
net core one
where we throw in all our services in
there
so you can easily just add another
hosted service in there if you if that's
how you wanted to do it
or
we we also have a an event aggregator um
or i think you might call the mediator
pattern pattern antenna system
um which gets which we have events that
go into it already when the coin is
received when the payment is received
when an invoice status changes all that
stuff
um which could uh trigger something else
for example we we also have web hooks in
there so when a payment is received on a
wallet it can trigger something external
btc pay
so
it all depends as well how you would
integrate wabi-sabi
if it would be built inside if we would
be able to import some libraries
and uh loading them inside the btc pay
process
or if you would have an external daemon
and
we would be pinging it and doing the
coin mixes two dots
wait wait wait we could do libraries and
that would be a nuget package would be
good for btc
yeah that could be pretty cool
i think i think we could do it that way
um
if if you had for example a package
where basically you have all the base
functionality you need to trigger a coin
joint
uh not trigger actually we could just
induce the coin join client library
inside b2c pay
um
that will that would probably be the
best way to do it because when you run
i think currently you have the rpc that
you have to call and you know operate it
separately if it's built into the
process of btcp that would be pretty
crazy like you can do
like the wall and send page we could
probably
either wrap it inside
uh
wrap the functionality around
your coin joint mechanism that's gonna
happen where you'll be able to do a uh
a payment from a coin join that would be
pretty cool
um but anyway in terms of technicals
um if you have a library that we can
run
as a as a background service inside the
code base of btc beta that would be
perfect
so i i explored i actually asked
zuckson to explore this to me and
he said
um
btc
bay wants to keep things lean and
and that's why
uh nuget library would not be a
good idea
um
yes um but
we want to keep things lean but if it's
a plug-in then it doesn't matter because
you can import a nougat library inside
the plugin
which
is just loaded as a as an on an
individual level
so that would be would become opt-in
instead of just uh having it lying in
the background in the b2c code base
um one example of a so basically our
plugin system is just
somebody create somebody references a a
few nougat libraries from btc pay we
have
i think it's called btc pay server dot
abstractions
and
basically you will implement an ibtcp
server plugin
inside that there is a methods which is
like i think it's called configure where
you can just add stuff to the dependency
injection container
and
you're free to do whatever you want from
at that point it's like you can add ui
pages you can add hosted services
running
uh throughout the entire lifetime of btc
pay
um you can listen to events
internal events that happen in btc pay
that you would not be able to
to do through
web hooks inside through the
btc pays
api um so you can go wild with that um
and the best part about it is
that the code would not
live inside the code base of btc pay it
would just be a plug-in that somebody
just uploads inside btc
and it runs on their server only
lucas do you have any ideas on
implementation
the way we've been writing it should be
amenable to reuse in that way i think it
boils down to
like how deeply can you integrate
um
in a way that satisfies the constraints
so for example if the
btc code
makes assumptions about like what kind
of inputs you can include and the
coordinator is going to reject that
later on because i don't know we don't
support
for starters or only paid a witness
pubkey hash or something like those
arbitrary constraints are probably going
to be the main source of friction like
how do you make sure that you can
actually drop in something that's
uh strictly a subset of the
functionality that's already available
internally but as long as that is not
insurmountable i think it should just
work like it's just a matter of
wrapping the internal like wabi-sabi
library implementation making sure it's
public of course first and and uh making
use of that and the hypothetical plug-in
yeah that would be that would be nice
because
any constraints in the software can be
done on your end so
when you wrap your wabi-sabi nuget
library inside the plug-in
code base you can just
like only listen to
when only listen to payments that come
in
on the stores wallets if it's a specific
type of script or something like that so
you can restrict it based to your
you know customize to your needs
we obviously don't have a lot of stuff
exposed inside btc pay right now
but
it should be quite possible like you'll
have access to for example
uh nba explorer if you wanted to um and
you know the the
utxos available and all that stuff so
you could completely bypass any
restrictions inside the btcp ui and
build your own
uh wallet send ui if you need it to or
just replace it entirely
it's quite like it should be quite
capable of doing like a
174 workflow
that should be more than
yeah
and which one is that again bit which
one
uh that should be compatible yeah for
sure we already have full pspt support
in there anyway like the entire what the
entire wallet sending system is using
pspts internally and
we expose them
i think it's like
you first go on a send page and then you
can say
uh create a transaction or sign it
directly at that point and it'll just
show you a sign psbt and then you can
say either broadcast it or do a page
join or something like that so it's
already
in that in that style like even in the
explorer exposes everything through
psbt's if you wanted to avoid the wallet
cent page
uh might it be useful to have output
script descriptors here so that for
example the btc pay wallet can just get
the excite private key and script to the
wasabi client
which then adds this key to its wallet
and
signs the conjurer
i didn't understand that
you you have output description uh
you're using output descriptors on your
end
uh no not yet but i'm curious if it
would be useful basically then this way
how wasabi can use its own signing magic
right and does not need to rely on bbc
signing
stuff right because there are some
nuances uh in conjunction
uh yeah yeah for sure um
so then we kind of just get the private
key from bbc basically
yeah you can do it you could like the
hot wallet system in btcp is the hot
wallet
uh system is not even inside be on the
b2c pay level it's on the amb explorer
level
so you can get the key completely
separately of b2c pay
as long as it's a hot wallet obviously
um
yeah no there's no issue there for sure
and for in terms of output descriptors
you don't technically need it um
because well btc so first first of the
store set up in btc it supports
importing an output descriptor
with some constraints to it
that it has to be hd
and
i forgot what else there is
basically it can be like a wrapped one
or something
yeah there's
there is some basic support but we
converted to a to our internal format
which is on the npx level uh but it's
not it's nothing complicated so
you can
quite easily map it to whatever you need
and then how about having a p2 endpoint
functionality in this
whatsapp what we saw be plugin
what do you think
a p2 endpoint well i mean there is
already pay to endpoint support than
in btc pay
i'm just curious on
i guess if you wanted to do if you
wanted to replace
the default behavior for patreon joined
and how we suggest utxos
and the page proposal itself
um you could you could just overall just
say
screw this implementation and just
replace it with your own using
dependency injection of some sort
um
with whatever you provide in the plug-in
so you can probably just say
um replace the entire page rain
receiver end point with with our own
wabi-sabi endpoint if you have something
very specific in mind because i i i'm
not sure what if you do
so
it's quite flexible i think everything
should be
like you can you can hack your way to
any functionality you want most likely
if you if you're good enough with
mastering the dependency injection
container
yeah yeah it will be a replacement of
page one it would guess
uh
it's basically like
both sender and receiver provide inputs
but also hundreds of other users provide
inputs in the wallabies i'll be
transaction
so
but it wouldn't be a it wouldn't be a p
a 78 one so
exactly
i mean you could
yeah go ahead
i have a question for you andrew and
about the
page on implementation but no knowing
the implementation the
the trend and the usage do you have any
numbers that you can share with us about
how many
how this feature is being used in the
real world by people
adoption
well i would tell you but if i if i
could tell you i think we would have
done something wrong because we have no
tracking system in there
um we have we have no analytics on
anything so we have no clue how people
use btc
oh but
but you you provide i probably i'm not
sure but
support people make questions so you
have some intuition of how this can be
using
in reality because it's like it's like
wasabi for example if we never receive
any
nobody asked about a feature nobody have
a problem with the feature nobody well
that probably nobody is using it right
yeah i i would say that
questions around patreon are quite low
um
but i also feel like that stems from the
lack of
motivation from a merchant point of view
um right now we have the most
primitive version of a patreon you can
do it in terms of bip78 functionality
that we can support
um
i have worked on i have worked on
some
private consulting stuff around
dip 78 where
i don't think it's out yet at all but
where i've worked on batch transactions
and
output substitution and all that stuff
so
and
it will be quite more
beneficial to a merchant to use these
kind of things in the future
in terms of life
uh what vicente merchant
why is
so they have to opt into this feature
why
is there something wrong with this
yes uh so the main detraction of it
in terms of us promoting it is the
hot wallet
uh requirement
obviously that's like
we don't want people to just decidedly
create a store
uh configure walls and just
automatically have a hot wallet that's
just
too
not risky but it's just
you know people already have always had
the option to
have a watch-only wallet inside b2c pay
and never risk their funds getting
stolen
so all of a sudden we're promoting the
opposite of that with with pay joints so
for me but
how about if the user opts into doing a
hot wallet then the default is patreon
activated
yeah
it's two separates
yeah that's that's a good idea actually
uh from mine i think that's a good thing
uh
i i do think that
i want to you know instead of just
enabling it by default only i also want
it to be
like incentive based
and that's you know once you start like
if you have
we already have a refund feature inside
btc pay and you already have merchants
sending transactions from inside btc
page wallet
so the idea is that we grab those and we
start batching them
inside
inside the
pay joints so that they save on fees
um and then after that as well there's
also the parts um where
you can eventually we want to have a way
to support multiple wallet script types
so you'd have segwit and
and p2sh on top of that
two separate wallets with generally
generating two
uh two addresses
so the default address would be p2sh
based and if they do a pay join
it would automatically upgrade and
substitute the address with the secret
one
that would also save on fees
what else is there also basically just
substituting
uh outputs
let's see how was it basically uh do if
uh if a pageant happens and you've got
the right circumstances
you can just die direct
redirect the the payment being done
to a pending transfer that you wanted to
do so it becomes kind of like a like a
three-party coin joint where you as a
merchant is not even involved in the
transaction because you just use inputs
from
from the person sending you money
um there's there's a lot of stuff that i
wish would be included obviously but it
just takes a lot of time and effort
um we'll get to it eventually but you
know things take forever
so let me ask one more thing that's
that's my last question regarding this
topic which is again a practical one
uh an other
question i had and i did not investigate
it but i hope you you guys did that
bit 21 you whereas pedro in your urls
are just an extension of big 21 urls
so now the question arises that
you know
wallets those are compatible with beep
21 urls
how do they
behave when they see a pageant url
do they throw an exception
do they just dismiss the page or import
of their url or
or did you did any anyone here uh
try to investigate that
yeah i i've checked a few wallets and a
few code bases around it
um for the most part i would say like
i forgot the actual numbers
but i would easily say like 90 of all
wallets would just if they don't support
paging they would just ignore it i've
seen some cases where where it crashed
because it expected the string and then
basically if you add an ampersand to it
it would just not recognize it and crash
but that's like a deeper issue as well
uh basically it was expecting that the
bip 21 url was just
uh bitcoin colon address
uh and then the amount and nothing else
like if you even added a label it would
crash so that was even a deeper bug on
their end
um but in most cases there was no issue
yep that's all i remember
all these fields are optional the wallet
don't doesn't understand it they just
should just be skipped
yeah exactly that's that's one of the
main things that i liked about bip79
um so bip 21 is you know nice and simple
at least so people know what the hell it
is and when they look at it
it's not too scary um i know that uh who
was i think it was
wax swing that had it on he had the gist
with
and a small discussion about a format
for join market before
before 579 i don't even remember if it
was before or after bip 79 was announced
um where they would have like
the three
like i think i think was address
endpoint in the mount with like comma
separated but that would not have been
nice to to share around either
um even just for copy pasting or trying
to highlight the text with a double
click or something that would have
failed
at least with bip 21 it's nice and easy
you can see that it's all one long
string and it's people are familiar with
the string as well with the string
format
um and also with bib 21 i
it it allows you to just expand it even
more if you wanted to
so if you wanted to change communication
uh for a bit for
for the pay joint so from
from uh http endpoint it would just be i
don't know like you say pj
communications or something and then
you'd say equals qr or something
or
or nfc or bluetooth and then you just
scan the network or you you make your
phone emits and
nfc data and then you just tap it with
another phone or something like that
that so those stuff is
completely possible if you just extend
it with
minor opt-in
opt-in layers
all right thank you so there are some
other guests in the quad too so max
would you like to
you have like do a transition
yes so of course
feel free to stay in if you still want
to contribute and hang out i was super
helpful so far though already so thanks
for that
um
we're also joined i think it's ben
kaufman and moritz uh they're both here
and
these guys are tinkering on the amazing
spectre wallet
which is kind of a graphical user
interface on top of the bitcoin core
infrastructure
and i think that's a very promising
project too so how are you both doing
not too bad i think uh ben is um
trying three times at the same time
listening in posting and doing the
new release but um
i wouldn't expect anything
else that's good multitasking
yeah yeah i'm doing good here
and drinking a beer
yeah
um yeah it's really great i'm i was
talking to
max last week about what what's
happening at um
and
it was it was
it's really interesting what's what's
what's going on with you guys and um
especially like um
how how you're working on the on the
better your ex now and
the next release and stuff so
very excited about that
thanks and welcome guys
and happy for joining us
um maybe
by the way
can i can i ask a question for because
now we we are
here uh a couple of uh wallet developers
and i would like to know
what do you think is
what
we need to improve
in the
standards or collaborations or what can
we do to
to make
the
the walls more
compatible if you want
more easy to
to interoperate
and
of course i i prefer to to know about
privacy but
i understand
that's probably not the
the main focus of all the wallets
but
just to know about that what do you
think
i guess it's just a lot of more uh
communication i think there is
not not really
uh a very you know central way to to
coordinate stuff um to uh set standards
for for stuff for i don't know for
example backups
uh stuff like that
so it's kind of very very um spread
around
um which i guess makes sense but it
would be uh quite easier
i think if it would there would be like
some
uh more standards
i guess for that
i think it's also just a matter of
someone picking up the slack and
actually doing it
i mean for example andrew shell with
hardware wallet interface
right that's
you know the concept is obvious but
it just took a while until someone
finally did it but no pretty much every
wallet is compatible with it
yeah yeah also
so for example just just for to be
a bit more concrete probably in my
questions for example do you think that
um
if we
all implement uh output descriptors for
example
could that help or do you think that
there is something more important that
we
can do
first for example you can you can say
hey you wasabi wallet i say we we think
you should do this first
it's perfectly okay to say something
like
that
yeah so i'm not sure i think
implementing out of descriptors would be
great for us because we already uh use
them natively
so if other wallets would would support
that too then i think that would be a
great standard to to move to
um but no i don't have anything else
like more specific in mind
okay and sorry and
for example we have been
discussing about pay joint right uh
minutes ago
i don't know if you were here but
um
well
uh
you know um
i'm not sure but it seems to me probably
um
a page on is
it was
um
invented or designed with the idea of
of being useful for merchants i don't
know if that is so true for normal users
i mean if i if my wallet because yes i
understand
mertens has a server that is running all
the time and it has a
web server
and
all that kind of stuff that may
make it
makes it uh
ideal for being a
patreon receiver right probably a mobile
wallet is not a good
um
example
do you think
pen to endpoint have some future
uh so i didn't research about it much
but yeah i think so i think
again i'm not for for specter uh it's
not really uh a tool for you know for a
lot of views uh from for merchants like
btc base server would
uh but i still think it it could be a
useful tool for some users
do you have it implemented now
uh no not yet uh we're looking to to
have that but just not enough time again
well i think here comes one one of the
crooks with spectre specifically is that
you focus on multi signatures and then i
would guess the vast amount of bitcoin
hold inspector is protected by multisig
which is that's just a guess
um and that makes coin joins of any type
more complicated even two-party
conjoints like page lines
what do you think patrons with
multi-stick is that even doable
uh i've i really didn't look into that
uh probably stephan i think did look
into that but you'd have to ask him um
so yeah i'm really not sure how
difficult would that be
andrew i i do think that yeah i do think
that patreon is possible with multisig
but the issue comes
where
it's really hard because you have to
match basically the the sender and the
receiver have to have the same script
types
so if the sender has multisig and the
receiver has doesn't isn't using
multisig and he doesn't have a
uh output an output substitution
location to
to a matching multisig uh script type
then you can't really you'll have a
fingerprint on the page right
transaction so that's
usually not very effective and the usage
on multisig will obviously
most merchants probably don't use
multisig and if you have a page on
receiver server with a multi-stick hot
wallet setup that's kind of
stupid i think yeah
so
um but i guess if you wait for taproot i
guess that's that would be completely
fine for multi-stick pay joints
require the non-ownership proof
right but stephan figured out um
i i think you could the attacker could
still steal money even if it's only
youtube party coin join if you cannot
prove that the other utxo is not from
this wallet
so i guess the same applies for multisig
on hardware wallets or even single sec
carter wallet day joints
it's probably not worth spending time on
well i would like to know if
if
the market is is requesting this
kind of features
or if it is just that some kind of
developers
masturbation you know that we want to
have this complex
uh algorithm
it and it's it's hard to know right
because from wasabi
our focus is
precisely to not to know i mean we don't
want to know so it's hard but probably i
don't know if you have more information
probably you have a um
i don't know
he probably you know more about your
users probably not but i would like to
know if you know something about it
uh i we have
at least inspector we also have no
analytics no data whatsoever
so
not really
uh so just just from talking to users
we do have a
few users asking about it
but i have no idea if they ask him about
it because they heard about it and they
don't really know what it is or because
they really know what it is and want to
use it so i have no idea
yeah from from my end it's
some people ask about it because they
see it in the ui but the not a lot of
people have an idea of what it does
um
but the idea of having a pay joint
that's camp with a with a payment
destination that's backwards compatible
so you know just the standard 21 is
that you can increase adoption without
harming any
any usage
and the idea is
eventually it becomes you know
worthwhile to a merchant that's running
a 24 7 server but
from uh from what you mentioned as well
like a mobile wallet it's uh you can't
just you could do it you could always
just spin up a tor circuit and all that
magic
but if you're in in close proximity you
can't even do it with just
uh qr code scanning and all that stuff
or nfc or some other p2p
communication that you do between
wallets
and it
from my point of view at least
it's not as complicated as you make it
out to be
it's literally like
two to a two process job right so you
receive a you receive a bit 21 you send
it at pspt over there okay maybe it's a
bit more more of a more steps but it's
you receive a destination to pay
you create a transaction that pays it
send it over and then you receive a a
pay joint transaction that you can
or
or don't want to proceed with
and it's just psbt
uh parsing and then the business logic
on top of that
well i agree that there are a lot of
users who just have mobile wallets or
decibels that shut down properly
but i think a decent percentage or at
least a decent absolute number of
bitcoin users have their own server or
their own big control note
uh probably running 24 7 in the
background so it's still i think a
decent
potential user base that might be well
suitable for these pay joints and to be
honest i think that's all that we need
right we don't need every user to run
pay join all the time we just need to
have the threats that the small
percentage of users run day joints to
already think the analysis
yeah exactly and okay do we i mean
what what is that small percentage
at one percent
i mean
they are already operating with
probabilities right
and 99 percent probabilities i think is
as good as
as any other
assumptions they have so
so i don't know
we need 10 percent 90 probability
not that good so maybe we should have
more no
yeah i i do think it needs to be more
than one percent for sure
to even make a dent in anything even
from just their own perspe
perception right of
how these things operate
um and also they wouldn't even figure it
out at that point if you have if you
have the specification
nailed down well enough that the
fingerprinting is not happening
then you
none of us will know really that there
is a 1 10 chance of
analytics poisoning happening through to
pay joint transactions
um
yeah
i i do think we can there the the best
way to look at it is just
patron on its own is probably not going
to do the dents that you wanted to
but it was part of a diverse a
diverse selection of tools
that you can use that as as people use
collectively in in their own little
ecosystems
they probably add up enough to make the
dent that you want wanted to
i just wish we'd be able to see the
clusters on
to to actually see how if they're
actually getting poisoned somehow or not
on
on private uh analytics software but
we'll never know right so
it's it's way too early to write on page
ones i mean
but
you know i think the hurdle is
is the for the user adoption is the user
experience
i mean
sir it's nice to have have this on the
merchant side but
that
i i don't know what percentage of
bitcoin transactions would be we'd
be the
big 21 urs but i think it's even smaller
than one percent
you think so i i i think the 21 is quite
used like uh from our ends our qr code
has always been 21 because it adds the
amounts to it um
we only have a very small percentage of
people
that use the address directly and the
amounts
separately um
because your
your service is for merchants
yeah yeah that's true
um
it's i mean
he has a good point right wasabi could
as well just draw a qr code with the 21
uri
and patreon enabled okay yes yes yes yes
sorry yes yes
you're right i completely missed that
so it doesn't have to be yeah it can be
just a qr code
can't
can it be
because
can other wallets read it even if they
are not compatible with pay join
yes but they must be compatible with the
21 and a qr code reader
but yeah it should be a good requirement
i mean do they do that that's the
question right
they
from all the wallets i've seen so far
they've all supported bit 21.
uh obviously from wasabi side you
probably would not add an amount you'd
only have the bitcoin address there i'm
guessing
okay okay that's very good then i i
withdraw
the strength from my opinion and
and yeah i think my argument doesn't all
that that much because there are fewer
quotes yeah sure
i have and again i think it's also a
usability
thing right i think if more wallets
especially wasabi would be able to click
on the link
and then be opened like the bitcoin uri
is supposed to work and if you have that
ux i would be sending around these
euro hits too
yeah can i
yeah
sure go ahead i was gonna change stupid
uh sure so i mean bitcoin the
even inside btc pay we we actually have
some naive implementation for
um natively opening bitcoin uris
basically browsers allow you to
hook onto
uri schemes and then they will open to a
specific url that you set them to
um so
going back to the plug-in thing
um if wabi-sabi is running
inside of the plug-in system we can even
divert
a url link to open up
in the wallet sent using what we savvy
to do the coin join to the payment
destination through it
yeah that might be kind of uh another
way
to connect wasabi and btc pay in a
bridge so you have run wasabi separately
and btp separately
and you can somehow manage in the gui of
wasabi the backend server of bbc pay
maybe you stop what you mean a bit
andrew
i was talking more like um if you were
running wabi-sabi embedded inside btcpa
directly
then you would be able to
use the bitcoin uri functionality
directly with wabi-sabi as well
um
obviously that's a bit more
intricate i guess in implementation
details
okay what's the next topic adam
oh i i wanted to ask more
if if he could talk about the
history of spectre
rather than the inspector like like
how did how did everything
yeah like like like when did you think
about it why if it's the mission
you know what i mean just the history
lesson okay
wow and it's not going to be a big
history lesson it was well
i started out with
in 2017 with the idea that there should
be better hardware wallets and i was
struggling to find the right technical
guide to start it and it took me like a
year
and then we were in portugal in lisbon
at the conference where you announced
wazabi wallet
and um yes i was sort of confused by you
on the stage there with the with the
with the pullover and stuff and
was just wrapping my mind around what's
coinjoin and what's going on there and i
met stephan at the party in the evening
and he was like hey you're a business
guy and what the heck and you want to do
a hardware wallet and then yes he showed
me some prototypes and i got really
excited and
yes then we partnered together in the
company
but
yes and then we're we weren't really
sure where to start and how to start so
we started working with the fraunhofer
institute which is the leading german
cyber security institute so like
infineon and siemens and everybody goes
there and we're just discussing some
chip designs and had everything really
nicely laid out and then we started
talking to vcs and
started to figure out that we don't
like this whole vc story so much because
they like blockchain and tokens and are
not into hardware because hardware
doesn't scale
and
then also not into open source because
then they don't control the ip so things
got
uh yes in 2019 in the summer i really
had to realize that okay we have some
really good prototype and
sleepon is doing great work but the
stuff that we want to do we don't get to
finance another conditions we wanted and
i already invested some company as a
money in the company
and then
yes then we saw hwi and i never i just
basically asked steven like okay when we
have a hardware what what's gonna be our
desktop app and we couldn't find the
desktop up we wanted to use with
a little bit like
uh cold card but you really wanted to
have a desktop app with it and then i
was just poking stupid noob questions
into sleepon and um was figuring out
with him okay you can basically do a lot
with the almost everything with the
bitcoin core node and i always felt like
this feeling that people especially at
technical conferences or anywhere else
that goes hey you have to run your node
and you have to use your node and check
your utxos and stuff
and um
and i always felt bad because i had the
computer at home there was bitcoin call
running but i wasn't really using it so
and then we we
sleep and said yes i can do a little
prototype and wrap this around and we
can make qr code gapped and pspt
transactions and then keith mukhai a guy
from chicago came in in just
over a week prototyped ledger and
trether support i think into it and keep
key
and then we could do multi-sig and and
it got really really interesting
but um steven is excellent at
prototyping
and then
really building it out took us done from
the say autumn september 2019
really to really launch it was in august
last year
and along the way um i was very happy
because um kim neunard was joining us
first and
then also ben came around after
advancing bitcoin in london in march
and
it was a tremendous help and and
high energy great feature ideas
implementing a lot and so we have a
really nice team now with stephan which
is which is really a
great great technical guy and and and
brainy and then the two other guys also
very smart and um
so i'm i'm like there
yeah i i like to support what we're
doing so at the moment the the business
model what we are doing is really that's
we building specter desktop
and on the
we have like an enterprise site where
companies come to us like a custodian or
a bitcoin development company or
specific uh
enterprises who want hardware or
firmware solutions and we build that for
it and this pays the bills
it's not too much and um
yes so we are using the enterprise side
to pay the bills and and try to make
expected desktop better and
of course
um
the the project is will be
like let's see how this works with this
enterprise side business model and i'm
i'm ready to to keep supporting it we're
getting some interest from vcs now
but i i don't know if if
if this is really the the best way
forward and then
because i think when you once start the
vc route and they want to push you into
the next series a b c d and then you
have to offer an exit or something so
i don't know if it's really well aligned
to how to to to
to
become a vc finance project
and so i'm i'm a little bit puzzled with
that
maybe you have thoughts on that but this
is where we stand so i think ben is
currently working on a packaged core
node into
spectre so that you can have a one-click
install on a prune node
and um
also like
tour integration
so and i think then we are quite ready
in the feature set and of course we're
looking for business models also inspect
the desktop
where we could uh integrate let's say uh
one instance was i was discussing with
max
um uh like a api for for conjoined
vasavi coinjoin where we would direct
our users into your coinjoin or service
integrations with uh collaborative
custody or or something like
peer-to-peer exchange so
this is something we think about but
it's um it's it's it's still quite early
yeah so that's the story
nice
um
i i would have like more more
maybe ben can answer that too but like
how
would you
like to get wasabi or wabi-sabi
because you don't really have a plug-in
system like btc pay so what technical
approach would you guys think of what
would you like
yeah so we're trying to to work on the
plug-in system actually so it's mostly
uh kim
from our team that is uh working on that
um so yeah we'll probably try to to go
with that approach but it's still uh
underworked so
okay cool
you didn't know that
but like what's what stuff would you
need from from like the wasabi
client that you could use
um so i'm not really sure i i guess
basically just an rpc server with with
all the functionality would suffice
probably
um but then in the way that the rpc
server manages the wallet that you have
in bitcoin core
sorry
i mean you do all the signing and stuff
with bitcoin core right
yeah yeah
so that means if you would have some
wasabi rpc server
who would do the signing would it be the
wasabi rpc server that signs or the
bitcoin core node
i guess it depends so whatever is is
needed uh if it's needed to be through
wasabi then then wasabi i think we can
we can work through that
by the way just for max
um you know max we have to
implement an external signal because
um
if you want to sign your your coin join
with your hardware wallet for example
automatically let's say
and wasabi has to allow that so
if you want for example that bitcoin
core
sign a transaction for you you will just
have to create the external assignment
it's a technical detail that
just yeah that's a good point
but just as a quick note then bitcoin
core also needs to understand the
non-ownership proofs right because
otherwise external signing is not secure
no designer the i mean you don't need to
well it's uh it's a
i think probably it's not for this meat
but i think it's not a problem
i don't know like what what i want to
come out with this question is if we
want to get wasabi in a spectre wallet
how much do we actually need to
contribute to bitcoin core just because
vector will use bitcoin core a lot
uh yeah i'm really not sure to be honest
so i didn't really look into how wasabi
would work so i
can't really give an answer right now
yeah i think no one can i think we don't
even know no yes
probably i'm wrong but
i think the only thing that you really
need is to
the
wasabi to know the expat key
right
um and
oh no
no sorry because it it well probably a a
an expat key that is known by
by it can call
and
implement an external signer the only
thing i'm not 100 sure how is to create
all the
the
addresses right
and
well
probably that's not a problem either
no it's it is possible yes it is
possible it's just we have to think a
bit but
it's not a problem i'm sure
anyway i would like to know what
what is the the
spectre team working on now and what
what i don't know if that is possible to
know if the surprise for their
their users but
um what are you doing
yeah so right now uh we just finished
with uh with this uh addition as as
maurice mentioned of bitcoin core and
spec and uh torr into spectre
so basically just packaging them so it's
uh
basically instant setup
uh we still have some some factoring to
to do right now so just cleaning up some
some stuff we were delaying uh for a bit
uh after that uh we are looking on on
stuff like liquid but we still uh don't
don't know for sure what where what
we're going to do next
so kind of going with it
yeah i think also with the release of
the package note we will do some
refactoring and cleaning up the whole
code base
so this is what's important to kim and
and and
and stephan and
i hope also to ben because ben is all
like
ben is all already um like
he loves new features let's say so
but um
so um
but we are quite there with the features
i guess and yes and then it's it's a
kind of a strategic decision what we
want to do first like focus on
integrations or
um
[Music]
at add new new bitcoin features like
lightning or liquid i think liquid is
quite interesting
um i don't know about about you guys
is this something where wasabi is also
thinking about or is it is it that are
you very focused on just uh pure
um
bitcoin unshame solutions
it would actually be cool to get a
confidential transaction coin joint
implementation running on liquid
uh i i should have counted the number of
times that we said during the wasabi
research clubs like let's just use
monero with ct and green signature that
makes everything easier
no but yeah
the liquid coin joint theme i think
metal delve
tweeted about it i mean we discussed it
already like uh maybe a half a year ago
it's it's
yeah it's it's a it's another
possibility that we could could do also
to complement like the whole privacy
ecosystem a bit more
yes but it's it's quite
quite a little bit away there's like the
liquid stuff is interesting but there
has to be some cleaning up and and and
iterations and hardware support and it's
it's not quite there yet for
for for that
yeah but to give a quick summary on
second player protocols in wasabi uh i
think first is priority to figure out
all the mistakes of the first layer
and that's already a ton of work
and then i mean everyone has to
implement lighting probably um
so sooner or later it will come but we
want to implement lightning network
right and like with
all the privacy focuses that we have on
chain so far
and that's just
impossible nowadays
yes and after after that we have to find
all the problems in second layer because
lining is is probably too far of
what
it was
promised right is
there a lot of details that can
compromise
the privacy of the transaction
and
yes we are not
close to
to to fix that in fact
we didn't start it yet
yeah tricky
yeah that's that's that's a good point
we didn't even started yet
that's it's it's very tempting to to
look at the different stuff and then do
this and that and i think this was
something
maybe it was in the first year a little
bit like tricky for us as a team to
figure out because we were playing with
a lightning app
and we were
looking into the hardware stuff really
really deep and and spent quite some
money on on time on the whole chip
design and and stuff and
then we sort of
said okay let's let's
also with the hardware like okay uh
they don't want to finance us okay um i
think we had one meeting with an
investor who wanted to buy us and um
we were a little tipsy let's say a
little drunk and sleepon got angry
and
he like he got bullish and went deeper
and i don't know what he does but he he
hacked me sort of and then we were like
yeah let's do this and
i was like i put in another 50k or 100k
and let's let's um let's let's do it the
whole hardware thing do it yourself and
so this is how expected diy then sort of
was born
and
now we're doing quite well we have the
smart card support
and stuff so and we don't want to
want to let go of that i think it's it's
a really nice
hardware wallet we get really really
good feedback so like everybody who gets
it and buys it and uses it says is his
favorite hardware wallet because of the
big screen about
the bitcoin only focus about all the
power features and it's still quite
simple so
and then yes this was
was was something where we really were
very stubborn but with the specter
desktop thing we are a little bit
opportunistic and see okay this this
really works and it's
so so
it's tricky not to get sidetracked
because there's so much stuff going on
in bitcoin and you really have to find
your niche and then really
refine your art in there and then and
make it the best possible solution so
it's
yeah it's it's tricky
and the new users are flooding in and
using coinbase
yes
i mean i don't know what we can do about
this it's just i mean
i was too using bitcoin at the beginning
and
it's just
i don't know it's just impossible i
think to
because they have this huge market and
we have the same here in austria with
bit panda but panda is a big exchange
here
and um
they have all the coins they have
all the vc money from vala ventures or
whatever they even doing radio spots
here in austria's my mom calls me say
like hey this bitcoin exchange
does and then every newspaper because
they are like the big austrian unicorn
now so
it's a it's a show on another level
and
it's
i don't know it's it's it's it's it's
really
strange and
we are we're hoping that um some bitcoin
only services will bootstrap maybe a
european version of so on bitcoin is
coming or something in germany or in
austria so
yeah relays is quite quite nice but
expensive and they have the problem that
they're doing everything on chain so i
think two weeks ago
and they had to shut down the service
for a couple of days because
the exchange there the back end exchange
they're working with
was
wasn't wasn't supporting the high fee so
there was some kind of argument about
the feast there and
yes so i mean that the pressure on
liquid and lightning to come will be
will be where we will be strong in six
months holy holy moly
yeah
i mean liquid is kind of an easy
solution to the p pressure right
specifically for traders high frequency
transaction makers in general
yeah um i wanted to ask the follow-up
question um it's interesting to see your
story with the hardware wallet work good
that you kept it up thanks for the
investment
um
this is painful it was painful i don't
know
i don't even want to know how many
bitcoins that was
i won't tell anybody
um no but um
what do you think are what percentage
are
roughly like what is the demand for the
pre-built spectre hardware that you
actually sell compared to people buying
the do-it-yourself parts and putting it
together
it's a small tinkerer and maker
community i would say so we sold about
but we wanted to keep the demand really
low because what we want to do is really
focus we don't want to go with specter
hardware wallet we don't want to go to
the mass market because it's uh
it's very competitive already outside
there
and then if you sell like 500 a thousand
of these pieces you make it's not a good
business you you you sell one of the
devices you earn a hundred euro and then
you have to
follow up with all the support and then
and then you have noobs buying it and
loops don't know about private keys and
nothing so we really want to focus on
the advanced bitcoins and the technical
bitcoiners but we get a fair amount of
messages now in the dms on on telegram
and the chats and our asking hey can i
buy a spector shield
and then i usually put them on the list
and let them wait a bit and if they come
back and say oh i really want to have to
expect a shield now then we are then we
are talking
otherwise it's uh it's it's very limited
so i don't know how many
specter diy or shield people are out
there maybe i should seat sign on ask
seat sign how many sold in u.s but it
wouldn't be more than
one or two hundred people i would say
something like this
okay interesting yeah yeah i bet that
scaling hardware production is a pain in
the
yeah i mean you have to basically you
you need some good operating business or
get some cash flows or whatever or have
a big vc investment and
but then you don't really have time so i
believe like we could not have developed
spectre hardware and the specter desktop
as it is today if we had vc money and
with vc money i think they want to have
after three months they want to see sort
of a crazy growth charts of whatever
you're doing
and um and and go go go go and growth
growth grows so i mean it took us sort
of 12 months to really figure out what
we want to what our niche is and what we
want to do
and then it took another sort of 12
months go to market to
really um
do to really have the product on the
market and no no no we have a good
product market fit i would say but
and we couldn't do that with with vc
money and
i i had also my learnings coming from
the business side you're very like
like people always tell you yes we see
money and you think that's the normal
way and then
you learn about bootstrapping the whole
thing and i mean there is a place where
we see money maybe later or whatever or
we can revisit the topic but at the
moment i'm quite happy with with it was
quite painful but it was uh it's it's
it's great and it's great to be on it on
such a team and make a sort of
contribution to bitcoin yeah
i would have one more
question leading to a bit of a different
topic
um
now that yuval especially is in here you
can maybe answer the technical sides of
this topic
um but first more it's could you maybe
share some of your kind of feature
requests
for a coordinator
fee revenue sharing model uh because
it's something we talked about i know
it's something you're interested in yeah
i saw the meme today and um with the
sewers canal and you were sort of um
you had an accident in the sewers canal
with feature good quests
so i don't want to too much put this out
there but i just want to say like we
would be really happy and really excited
if there would be
an api for for for your coin joint
implementation your upcoming
and
because we can direct the
our users to use um this this coin join
we can add a coin join wallet which
would use your back end in the in the
end so it would be really exciting to to
have sort of an integration there with
uh with your conjoined coordinator
yeah and like what are some of the um
like specifically on that featuring like
how are you envisioning it because i
think your kind of use case on how you
would use that thing would help us in
designing it properly
one more thing sorry i didn't get that
i can go a bit more into details with uh
with like what type of revenue sharing
what what different models you were
thinking um
just so that we get a use case and can
consider that in designing it
um on the technical end um i don't know
ben maybe you know how we um looking at
this with the with the other service
implementations but we would need some
kind of a way to to have a meter how
much
volume or which kind of volume we're
bringing to
um
we're bringing to the conjoint
coordinator but we of course we don't
want to
like the core features of spectre is
really
your node your verification
um your wallet infrastructure and
everything so on your infrastructure
which is your privacy and then your keys
your coins and all that interoperable
and quite user-friendly so we cannot
um
we cannot um
damage the privacy of our users there
so it would be like we need to secure um
like a proxy server going through one of
our or through a server that we operate
so uh i'm not technically enough to to
to
to expand on that
too much i guess then
maybe you know
ben is out i guess
yeah maybe you all can go a bit more
into the details of how wavisabi might
fix that
um i don't have any like concrete spec
or anything but um i mean in the way
that we model
um
like bitcoin mounts we're also modeling
weight units right now in order to make
sure that
um like the transaction ends up being
standard
uh we could
basically like
figure out some way of having additional
ways of quote spending credentials
on like specific
uh things that are not outputs like you
you register something that's
a pseudo output essentially and instead
of
the server appending that to the
transaction
it keeps him sort of um auditable
account of what you're spending this on
right is it a donation to some service
is it um a bounty for a bug that the
coordinator is involved in
or or something like that and i suppose
that different wallets could just come
with these you know configured to by
default you know donate
some share of excess uh
like the the suppressed change or maybe
some percentage of e uh would go towards
a specific you know entity
um but ultimately like
at the point where you hand off the
money to the coordinator
uh like
that's kind of a big trust assumption so
i think the coordinators need to or the
coordinators and the
entities receiving the money
need to be um
like trusted to some extent
um the advantage is if you can prove
that you know payments were made uh like
you could uh then correlate that to this
like audit log and and say like here's
the receipt
uh the the money that you asked to go to
like this bitcoin address or something
eventually did make it to there
okay so this is maybe somewhat of an
affiliation system
right where different people or projects
can get an affiliation code
might even be something humanly readable
right and then the user can
put that into the wallet either himself
or it's shipped by default in that
integration
so
the user like registers that affiliation
code
and there needs to be um
careful consideration of things like um
fingerprinting through timing attacks
like if you see that a certain unique
soul cluster
uh happens to be uh or a suspected
cluster happens to be used around a time
where coin joint transactions auditably
donate money to wikileaks or something
uh you know uh there's potential
circumstantial evidence that might not
even be true but might you know be used
uh
in a sort of like surveillance
capitalism type uh model uh of doing
business so
um like you need to consider those
things as well um
yeah if the payouts are to be verifiable
and transparent
i think an initial proof of concept
would probably be something like
and this is way down the line but
something like vote on your you know
wasabi feature and if we make sure to do
that um in a way that's privacy
preserving uh then it's probably gonna
be easier to generalize to um uh
you know add another layer of
auditability on top of that
which is now involving like multiple
entities
being paid by the same coordinator and
maybe like multiple coordinators
trusting each other to you know keep
honest accounts
okay
that's interesting
i also wonder about the legal
consequences of this but i actually
don't think that affiliation payouts are
of any legal concern
i mean sure you probably have to
like make some
smart accounting for it or
to get it above board but
it seems this is just a standard
business practice
yeah the legal stuff is a little bit
tricky we would have to check that i
mean
like
yeah
but as we don't operate the coordinator
ourselves
and we're just
offering like a service integration so
it's officially not our
our client to say so but there is no
client in them that's it's tricky it's
tricky
we would have to discuss with with maybe
some some legal guys there
yeah but this is maybe one note where
they feature requests that i hear from
you um like to not need or to not carry
the legal responsibility of running a
coordinator and earning revenue from
that
um
yeah
so this is something that has to be
considered to right that this is legally
solid and especially that there is no
legal burden on the
kind of affiliation users
yeah yeah
i mean
everything is legally solid that is
non-custodial
in any jurisdiction right now
yeah but you could argue that this
affiliation payout is getting custodial
because ck snacks gets the bitcoin onto
their own chain address
from the fees but then they oblige
themselves to forward that money to
crypto advanced company
right and in that meantime
yeah it might be considered but again
it's kind of like
uh
the user provided a uh like a coupon
code an affiliation voucher
and because of that either he gets a
discount or some money gets bored uh
i don't know i'm not a lawyer but
uh
yeah
yes you would would have probably to to
set up some kind of company in the right
jurisdiction also to
to mitigate this
tricky
yeah but i mean the feature would be
extremely useful if it would not require
the receiving party of that money to
need any legal setup like if this can
just be an anonymous individual in
cyberspace
uh
we don't care as long as somehow they're
the users say that that guy should get
some money
tricky tricky tricky
i actually think framing it as an
affiliation marketing scheme
is an interesting idea
i don't know
actually shinobi i hear i see her on the
call do you by any chance i have any
thoughts on that
and i see then gold wants to speak to
how's it going then
it's going well max uh yeah i have a
a pretty cool uh take on the
sharing there regarding uh if it's
custodial or not because i know the 2019
guidance from fincen
exempts
explicitly miners or
minor pool operators from
being money service businesses
so it seems like
it seems very similar in that if you're
sharing earnings
then
you're not a custodian i don't know if
anyone else has
read that or is familiar with that
aha that's interesting it has some
similarities still mining cool
and it's not just for the
like decentralized mining pools it
straight up says um
the person acting as the leader of the
pool claims the total amount mined and
receives fees from participants to be
authenticated and
it says that this
the cloud miner
it calls them a cloud miner and they
don't even need to be incorporated
um
i think yeah you can definitely draw
parallels
that's interesting thanks
but yeah i will probably talk to this in
length with some lawyers and
see how it goes
but actually right
maybe
maybe let's
go in some more interesting topics
which
would be yes please
which would be
the choice of lucas
oh well
well
my point is what i would like to
discuss is something that
it bothers me with all the wallets it
bothers me with wasabi too of course is
the
the incompatibilities between wallets
and also how to backup
the wallets
because you know if
if i want if you what sorry if you have
your wallet in i don't know um
myself
well probably you cannot recover it in
in another wallet
and you cannot recover your wasabi
wallet in mycelium and you cannot and
it's a big mess right
and also we have
different wallets
have different um metadata
or extra information that wants to
um store for example in wasabi we want a
good yeah
look we have
probably
some
small pieces of information to say even
i don't know
how the rest
of the ecosystem is dealing with with
this
so it feels like
yet coin wallets are
so innovative
today that
standards we don't even have yet time to
emerge
yes and last week
we or or the week before that we
discussed why we are in the situation
where we are right now um and basically
how this started with bitcoin core
having the
a pool of
key pairs and then it was a
vip 32 and then
vip 39 and
okay it works okay but it was designed
in my opinion it was designed
mostly for bitcoin call
right and
all the derivation path
and all the the thing for example i
don't know the the change the chain code
in vip 72 and all that stuff is
it's all something that it was not in my
opinion
and it was
probably
designed
without
uh
without knowing
how the
how other wallets can
um
about the needs of the the rest of the
the world it's probably because there
were no other words right it makes sense
but
i don't know i think you know
in lightning for example you have
you if you back up something you need to
back up also the channels in
multi-section wallets you need to back
up
not only the
one
pub key but you need to to back up the
other
pub keys too in order to be able to
to
re
recalculate the the
the thing that you see so it's
it's a problem i think
um
there are a lot of other things for
example just
if we want for example to create
a page on it right for of course we will
do it with uh with tor
but other wallets doesn't work with thor
and not it's a big mess so how do you
how do you see this do you see something
similar or it's just me
and
how are you
working around the problem
if you have the problem
it's a mess
output script descriptors solve a big
chunk of it
so i'm saying we need another standard
to collide all the standards so it's
it's going to be an organic process
right like if something becomes so good
that
every wallet
wants to implement then
then well every bullet is going to
implement because
the market is going to choose the
customer the wallets those
implement the stuff that they want
so i mean
i guess in the internet
i actually have no idea what happened
but there was this
opposition model right like that was
supposed to be the standardized
version of tcpip
maybe and and you know like it didn't go
that far
so
maybe just
just let the market to take care of
itself
well but we are the market
like the choices we make for wasabi have
meaningful impact and the outcome of
this
uh uh no no no because right now we are
talking about standardizing
we are not talking about like oh there
is that other product like output
descriptors which could make our wallet
so much better
uh now we are talking about well the
output descriptor seems to become the
standard or maybe not so
we should implement it because it might
be a standard you know
we we have to look at features not
standards
what problem does output descriptors
purport to solve
it gives you the an exact description
literally a definition
of under of both the script
um so it gives you all the information
you need to generate the script
uh and it works for example also with
extended public keys so it you once
defined the script and then you
interchangeably add the expert from
which the wallet can generate all the
individual public keys and the addresses
so it's like an extra peter and
superstar gene
yeah you basically end up with
with the xbob and uh and the keypad and
everything in one go right it's
especially useful for multi-stick
but you still end up losing you know all
the essential data that you need to back
up with
for lightning for example if that's one
of the scenarios you want to back up
uh any kind of metadata that you need so
like if you're if you're handling like
for wabi-sabi you've got logic around
um how much
how much depth you've had with your
trend with your coin joints that's
something quite important that you want
to save right
otherwise
you're you're kind of in the dark
afterwards
if you recover on a different machine we
just isn't there a gap limit field in
output script descriptors
no there isn't
they take this logic to its logical
accent the logical extent is that the
ultimate bitcoin standard is
it's not xbox key it's not output
descriptors it's not
not output descriptors plus more
information but it's like a standard
bitcoin wallet file
i'm more confused than when i asked the
question it is it the problems that
solve relate to
finding the script when do you lose the
script this is like for recovery
purposes it's usually best for like
interacting with outside wallets and
other wallets so that when the wallet
you're working with sends something
external it's it knows it's sending it
to the right derivation path the right
script type the right um x pub so that
whatever external wallet
it's going to wind up in the right place
and it's also
like importing keys to uh watch wallets
and like that
a way to look at it is also that the
openscript descriptors give you the
deterministic backup right so this is
the stuff they generate once a bullet
generation and from there on out you can
generate all the addresses
it does not include dynamic backups of
for example your labels who knows about
the addresses or your lightning network
channels and all these dynamic backups
need to be done
in a different way
okay thanks shinobi thanks max
yes but again again imagine you have
your
you import
right a couple of um output descriptors
in your wallet right
uh how do you back up that
in fact
uh
now we have other
12 words or 24 words
but an output descriptor
right
for a i don't know for one specific
script let's say
uh
there is no
it was not designed to be
let's say the wallet itself or or easy
to back up or no it was just
for interoperability basically
so think of it like your x-pub like it's
just another thing like your x-pub that
you have to keep track of um
like to pass around to the software
wallets you're using
right to answer the question that wasn't
asked like what problem does an x-pub
solve it helps you
connect a bunch of addresses together
without
keeping all of them i guess maybe the
problem that output descriptor solves is
it lets you do that but across
multiple derivation paths
yeah derivation paths script type like
it's super multiple derivations like you
could tell like you could tell it if i
if i remember everything correctly like
you could tell it to do like bec32
scripts on a totally different like
derivation path that's not standard for
bec32 and a wallet compatible with that
would just know like this is what i do
so it's like it's like a more flexible
equivalent of an x-pub that you plug
into wallets to play with
yeah but
i'll go ahead
and exports are only used basically in
the context of keys in wallets right
because most well most times we use just
single six and multisig but actually
what's happening is is that these are
all scripts and so alpha script
descriptors contrarily to something like
an expo is focused on displaying the
actual script that was used uh in to
lock up this bitcoin
so that's that's why it's more flexible
it can express any skirt type right yeah
yeah it basically replaces xbob wipe off
zip
any other vip 32 spec
yeah
yeah and it's right and right and also
multi six time blocks and like any
anything that you can put into a spread
basically
not exactly it's i think it's a subset
of manuscript for example so i think
manuscript is uh can do more stuff
but yeah it can do a lot
but i think that the the issue is that
it's still not enough
to do a universal bitcoin backup right
you need so much more data like if you
want to be efficient about it you need
so much more data
especially if you're handling privacy if
you're handling
coin joints all that data it's it's
still a central part of it it's still an
essential part of a wallet that you need
so
an output descriptor by itself is still
not enough it's only enough to save your
funds but not enough to preserve
essential data that you need stored
for for most wallets i would guess
yeah and the sad thing is that this this
important information is always going to
be dynamic and be created alongside with
the wallet is being lived right so this
is this is an issue i think that only
live backups control encrypted on some
other server for example
gosh well i mean honestly though it's
also just
as as flexible as output descriptors are
it's probably a bad idea to use them to
describe
very non-standard stuff right now
yeah
at least so many scriptures more along
the way
well but
my point about interoperability was
mostly because you know everybody is
creating their own technology
and
and some people
just don't stop and probably they are
right but they don't stop to to
to share the idea how to create a vip
they just write the
the
implementation and we end with this kind
of for example
white path
feedback
teapot and all that kind of crap and and
people using a completely um
non-standard derivation paths
and it's a huge mess and
that's
only for the
keys right i mean for the key derivation
algorithm
and
just imagine the rest i mean when you
want to to save something else i i don't
know what but
it's it's completely uh uh
a problem and now yeah
we have output descriptor but in my
opinion
it is for
for communication mostly it's not
something that you want to to use for
for backing up your your your wallet
the best way is to steal something like
the
vip 39 and
save your backup your words in in paper
or who knows but uh
well i mean yes to an extent right if
you want to back up in meat space then
recovery words are the best ux you're
gonna get but i mean maybe we can
transform an output script descriptor
into humanly readable words right i mean
that should just be an encoding issue
um but yeah also if like if you want to
do digital backups in cyberspace then
the output script descriptor makes sense
again
also like it's why like we
we shouldn't be conflating the word seed
with the output descriptor i mean that's
like conflating your private key backups
with the x pub like those can be
completely independent things and like
output descriptors are not trying to
replace your words they're trying to
replace the x pub and that public data
that doesn't put your money at risk
and like really things like this are
absolutely necessary to bridge those
gaps of everybody doing their own thing
and being incompatible like everyone
with their their own derivation paths
their own schemes output descriptors are
a way that you can bridge those together
so they actually work properly
well i mean is it is it actually correct
because you can actually store an expert
inside the output descriptors as far as
i remember
that is a
horrible idea who the put that in
that spec
no why it's useful too
i disagree i'm bombing out before i
start yelling shinobi i'm gonna ask you
to please not say stuff is good or bad
without explaining why it's not helpful
it's so confusing
this is the second time what do you mean
i don't think that why is it bad of a
key set should be made and transferred
around digitally if you're doing that it
should be done analog and it should be
transported between different security
devices i am not on board with the idea
of making multiple copies of private
keys and transferring them around
digitally on network devices i think
that's a horrible idea
i think it depends on the scope like
you're looking at i mean from my point
of view
it's like if i'm creating a wallet
that's going to have a hot wallet in it
wouldn't it be nice if i only have one
config one configuration item that i'm
just sitting with all the data you need
to create
the the derivation scheme the pathway
and uh private key that's you know
allocated to just this one xbox in one
go
no i think that you should have
everything but the private key and you
should have to pull that word seat out
and punch that in like i i do not like
the idea of private keys flying around
to the winds
so guys um i started documenting um some
of these uh wallet configuration files i
think most of you guys who are on there
spectre wasabi wallet um i also have
electrum um i wrote up the
just some typescript definitions and um
and outputted some json schema i don't
know if you guys are familiar with that
um the reason for that it was to like
look into this uh problem of like what
are similar within the wallet
and um uh in terms of like the
yeah the data that they're storing um
uh
uh unspent um
unspent uh
uh transaction outputs
um a list of transactions or some of
them
um
uh private keys etc etc
uh so there's like two categories
there's application specific
uh configurations right like app
settings and stuff
and then there's like the
things that are a bit more portable um
like the um utxos with the labels and
and whatnot um so yeah i just wanted to
add
i sent some links earlier in the chat as
well if you'd like to have a look at it
just to see what uh
just to compare
um
well in traditional shinobi fashion
since i slept in um
if there's nothing else anyone has to
say for the minute anyone feel like
catching you up in five seconds to what
i missed
ptcp is plugin with wabi-sabi and
spectre
i
rpc server
integration or spectre might use rpc
server and wasabi
okay so you're talking about bolting
wasabi i mean spectre on the wasabi onto
btc pay
yeah more like getting wabi-sabi inside
these wallets
okay so yeah okay so other wallets
hooking up to the wasabi api
not even just that i think
from the btc pay side in terms of
potential is more like embedding wasabi
inside btc
like it would be running in process
okay so there's two separate topics the
api plug-in and then embedding
and i think the third topic that we have
uh is dan gould with gen case which just
is basically like a wasabi fork that
wraps it
for ios so that's maybe dan could speak
a bit about that approach
sure yeah the main
piece of work that had to be done to
have that happen is
make
wasabi wallet a library that could be
pulled instead of
uh a whole run time
i forget who was talking about it
earlier maybe
maybe as moritz was asking if there's an
api available for wabi-sabi and the main
issue with
getting coinjoin functionality into a
wallet is that you have to do all the
crypto you have to have the
client for the protocol on the device so
we turn that into a library and then
from there
of course there are issues um
like
tor integration uh making sure that sock
server works
and getting neutrino to
function in the constraints of the
device but that's basically where we're
at we had a release last week that
reduced our
instability by 90
so i'm feeling good in general about the
direction and
definitely open to questions people have
um
we want to implement page join at some
point too
is that interesting thing there is that
you can have the ephemeral hidden
service
available
on your mobile device um which is open
like while you talk to someone else
even in the background
not all the time so it'd be totally like
you you can have it in the background to
some extent like if you went and send a
message to someone to send them your
hidden service address
at that time you could have it running
in the background but it wouldn't be
something you'd want open all the time i
don't think
so did you guys just
refactor the c sharp code base into the
library or did you like completely
rewrite it in something for ios like
sorry i'm not really too familiar with
it yeah it's it's refactored it like
we've got the same uh
tests we ripped hwi out for simplicity
for now
but it's the same c-sharp library and we
put a different front-end and different
uh
application lifecycle
management to work with the operating
system
okay so that should be
generally portable to any system
yeah it's forked from i believe
the
1.1.11
so the last major release of wasabi
all right so that sounds like a great
starting point for ripping apart and
putting in other things
yeah i mean it works we've been
operating since
june and
some people are fanatics
happy to get
more people
on board i think you'd be pleasantly
surprised and the ui is coming quite
quickly along
yeah i mean i was just excited to see
you guys fork it period and see somebody
besides wasabi running a coordinator
yeah anyone can access that as well it's
the
100th of a bitcoin denomination rather
than a 10th
that's posted on our
github hopefully we'll have a demo of
the whole
app and video rather than just the
coinjoin portion uh
sometime soon and i think
it'll make more sense when that comes
around
yeah it's kind of it's kind of
interesting the fun part from mayan is i
get to run the ios stuff and hack it
into a browser app from mine
i don't think you're very happy with
that one though then
i wonder
what's
like i wonder if you could connect it to
tor and get it to work as an alternate
to metamask you know if you had a
complete privacy wallet
in your browser
in lieu of metamask i don't know how i
guess syncing with the network would
also be difficult
um i don't know could you have a gig of
data that you store
in browser i don't see why not
i mean
right now
so okay so running it there's a bit of a
difference here you're still having the
server running on your computer like
that like the like a web server
so i i'm not running it it's running in
blazer but it's not running the web
assembly version so it's not completely
embedded into the browser
um
uh yeah we could we could run it into a
web assembly thing uh i think in the
future i think there's some crypto
missing from
from the dotnet
tree libraries i think dot net six will
fix that all and make it work properly
with no modifications
theory at least
there are like eight asterisks after
that statement
yeah
yeah so right right now it's completely
hacked into place so that it can run in
the browser just for easier testing and
prototyping
but it is saving it is synchronizing the
blockchain
true neutrino and saving it to
to the update on my on my windows
machine
i'm pretty sure it works on linux too
and i also kind of
hacked it around at one point i did
manage to get it running on android but
that wasn't
the most optimal
performance to say that like everything
was crashing all around me on that one
um but yeah you actually got wasabi
running in a browser
not
not really the ui was running yes yeah
what do you mean it definitely runs
yeah yeah
yes
yeah yeah terms and conditions apply
but yeah
it does
it does run and
to be fair i i really doubt we could
make it run into like this fake metal
mask
wasabi
crazy thing in the
in like a little tap thingy next to your
address bar that would be
i don't know i i feel stressed just
thinking about that so
that might be far-fetched but
even on ios we are running wasabi
essentially in the browser like
basically we have a hybrid web app and
that's what's happening
pretty much yeah
it's running blazer it's running a
blazer ui so
um and everything is running to a net
core
is it.net core or or mono and it's mono
so it's xamarin
yeah yeah i don't know how that's
everything is really in flux in this
like stack i think dot net six is gonna
push stuff around quite a lot
yeah
hopefully for the better
i mean could we potentially have a
desktop client
and a browser client
that use like the uh
that use the same app directory
basically
for sure
the
the browser one is actually running in
uh it's saving the
some of the data inside an app data
slash chain case folder
um i'm guessing
technically wasabi could kind of read
the same folder data i think it's the
same right then i i don't think it's
completely different in that regard
yeah all the caveats are around
just using the operating system it
doesn't use tor right now the one we
have on the browser does not install or
use tor that's like
one big issue but um as far as just
saving a json file yeah it can read the
same
uh
it can read the same blocks files and
wallet files and all that
index i mean i mean the tour part is not
that hard to do is just run the docker
container next to
next to it and just point the sox5
client to to it at that point right
or we could just embed it into the
server if we really wanted to but yeah
yeah it's not the point of chaincase at
this anyway so
uh the the main reason why why it's
running in a
in the browser
is just for faster prototyping just so
you don't have to wait for
the app to load on your phone and then
you have to try it out and then you
reload it and all that stuff
right we got hot reload in there through
the browser
yeah that too nice i got um
uh protector is able to run in the
browser as well right um at least the
development environment but how much of
the
um
yeah uh oh
yeah how much of the rest of it can run
in the browser
and is that like something that people
would want to do even
i mean in general it might be
interesting to connect to a remote
machine via the browser i'm not i'm not
sure is that in scope for this
discussion or is that a different
model
so so the browser is just for like uh
connecting to something like the remote
server or whatever yeah like write the
lightning or thunderhop or something
but that's something different right
it's just the browser web interface but
the actual stuff is running on the
server what you're talking about is that
the actual software is in the browser
itself
no no i was asking like uh to what
degree does it like kind of start and
stop um because i did get spectre um
because yes spector's uh ui is also uh
written in like
html um so the development environment
um
you can like if you spin it up it uh
it opens up a browser page and you can
access it um i just don't know how much
of the like back-end functions it's able
to
do in that version of it but um i think
more it's just gone i didn't see them so
you'd probably be the one to answer it
or then
ben is still here
yes yeah can you repeat the question
yeah so i got um spectre to run the
development environment in the browser
but i was just looking at the
configuration
page um i didn't like interact with like
try to set up a wallet or anything like
this so it's just asking since
everyone's on this topic of you know um
while it's running in the browser uh to
what degree can spectre run right now in
the browser
uh so with the browser i mean it's
everything runs in the browser so it's
it's basically inspector is a flask app
so
um yeah everything is on the on the um
on the front and side everything is you
know javascript html stuff
on the back end it's it's python and uh
this allows us to to use um some more
advanced stuff i guess
uh because yeah thor running tour and
stuff like that would
uh i'm not sure it would be possible
from from the browser itself i don't
think so
um but yeah so so the the browser code
is it's more for the ui i guess
do people um request having this like
like i said a request for wasabi or
spectre or
uh chain case whatever is there
like a demand for having these
browser-based wallets
um because like given the security
um
risks of it as well if you have
extensions
you know spying on the page and whatnot
um but is there a demand for it
i know people who operate with hundreds
of millions of dollars in ethereum
tokens in the browser
so
people really people really like using
uh browser extension wallets
random idea
if something goes into the browser
browser
that people are using for a web page
maybe that thing should only get a child
bip 85 key and it shouldn't be allowed
to touch the other keys
more generally like
so
what does a wallet do i think it has
like three layers of um usage
one of them is like this is what wallets
specialize in so
either you'd have something specific to
do with the blockchain layer
like wasabi does
or you have something that's um
like lightning notes that's another
example of something that's you know
specifically about the bitcoin protocol
but also extends to
uh smart contracts so
you're doing some application specific
script um bisque uses that as well
and then the third layer of kind of you
know wallet responsibilities are
managing like allowing you to
spread your credentials and physical
space in a way that's actually secure
follow some local policy and ideally in
the future those three layers should be
completely independent like you should
be able to compose your multisig policy
that you
uh i don't know define with your
business partners or something
uh including say a harder wallet
like
whatever um you should be able to
compose that with an application layer
so something like you know bisque that
actually needs to
uh make specific outputs of specific
contracts and you should be able to
compose that with a blockchain layer
wallet that manages for example network
level privacy
and in general helps to move funds
between um like actual uh sets of
credentials like allocate
which you utxos are spendable by which
uh specific uh uh policy keys
mm-hmm
because it's like yeah the it's like the
like what you just said then just blew
my mind like that is horrifying
like
segregate keys that touch a real browser
uh yeah i agree it's just like
people go
for the easiest
experience you know if they can end
three clicks
from watching a youtube video
install uh
you know infrastructure for their
business they'll do it
that just that blows my mind like that
like uh like i just cannot wrap my head
around that
when i bought my first bitcoin i got the
shield block wallet on an android tablet
sent the coins there and then
immediately put it in airplane mode turn
it off and let the charge died and just
left them there for like six months
because it's like holy everything
can steal these where do i put these
yeah i do i i don't know if it's gonna
change or or not i think
people will get wiser to
segregating keys but at the same time if
we have more people
on board
more people
are going to use solutions that exist in
the browser it's hard to say
it's definitely not
what i want to build right now right i
don't think it's the most secure
environment so i don't
think it's the best way to
spend resources
so i was hoping one project this weekend
on the fomo hackathon and it's a
lightning browser extension similar to
lightning jewel
and the idea there is that um yeah you
load in some macaroons and um
uh connect to your node and then you're
able to
pay for
content on the web using um this
extension with like prompts and you can
set allowances and and whatnot but this
one relies on um connecting to a
uh and authenticating to
like a remote node right
um versus like crypto stuff happening in
the browser
but i guess like the authentication
i guess the authentication tokens can
still be um or the macarons can still be
like hijacked but perhaps you can i'm
not too sure about like um the extent of
like permissions you can do in lightning
but maybe there's some kind of like rate
limiting or something um that you can
set on the macaroon
permissions
at the very least so macaroons support
what's called caveats where you can add
additional restrictions in uh like
object capability lingo uh that would be
called attenuating the capability so you
can like if you have a macaroon you know
how to produce valid macaroons
with additional constraints so you can
create another one that says like this
expires
and the default for the lightning
command line utility is to
uh only transmit tokens that expire
immediately but i mean you can apply the
same kind of approach to limiting the
macro and so you can figure into a
client and say
have it expire in a day or
something can we do by amount
i don't know if lightning supports that
specifically like lnd um
it's definitely possible in principle
with macaroons like you could invent
caveats for literally anything
you could you know
get very fine-grained with the actual
permissions like you could have a
specific endpoint like template or
something like that
to only allow a single use of a token to
make a specific payment or something
like that like in principle the
object capability model is like very
well suited for this kind of um
restriction of access rights in a way
that
allows validation between bits of
software
i like to use object capabilities
yeah i mean as long as you can rate
limit that in the sense where a user can
go to the real mode and stop things like
that's
infinitely better than just putting keys
in a browser
well
in principle i mean you would want to
just have
different like
the web wallet its job is to integrate
spending into your browsing experience
right its job is not necessarily
to manage uh node state or key material
or anything it's just responsible for
saying
what should be done right what what
transactions need
or what dxos need to come into existence
for my function to have been fulfilled
and they can delegate that behavior to a
lower level wallet that actually manages
um right like the the policies like what
sort of uh utxo selection are you doing
or you know
um i i think that's where the a lot of
the friction and
like interoperability exists like that
there's no
coherent separation between layers of
like responsibilities for different
wallets and then every wallet ends up
specializing in its own layer and kind
of neglects the other responsibilities
of
what an idealized kind of wallet
could be
would you be able to to do something
like um
set that a plugin up like that that
macaroon authenticated to a node on the
same machine
but then instead of handling
everything through that literally just
use a uri
request from the plugin to bring up the
actual wallet and authorize it there in
like a smooth flow
in that case you probably wouldn't need
permissions and stuff if it's in the url
right
yeah but i'm just thinking in terms of
like at least you have to
[Music]
you know
screw with the plug-in um
before it'll just start spamming uri
requests that you you know i mean
i don't so
at what point in the process is a urine
introduced and who generates it and who
queries it
well i'm saying like you instead of
like
handling things through purely like
macaroon authentication just go to the
plug-in click like you the user actively
clicks something and then that
authenticate with the node and launch
the uri if that authentication passes
um well the whole point of doing it that
other way so uh that would
in the macaroon like flow that would
kind of be like a third-party delegation
type thing
uh so if you have a certain capability
and and you can sign with a public key
then you can uh say uh like i vouch for
the bearer of this uh token
uh and the back end server can kind of
uh authenticate that
and
you know uh gate limit your uh your
access or uh
and for some uh caveats that the third
party uh imposes on the
on the token but like macaroons are
basically like a cookie they're
something that you attach to an existing
request so
um
like if you don't have the macaroon you
would be redirected to some page
potentially via such a uri where you
would be able to obtain that through
like a typical web flow
um that's kind of what was uh uh
described in the like the the paper
introducing them
i don't know what lightning supports
that
my only thinking and just have the
authentication before launching the uri
um
is so maybe you could just restrict uris
like that and not have
cheeky just launch like uri
requests for opening lightning payments
by default on pages everywhere or
something you know i mean yeah i think
that is like another big problem that we
have which um like if you have
wallets installed um
uh
they're all using the same name space
um
like
yeah so they're kind of like competing
and like okay so you would just have
like five lightning wallets open if you
had a bunch installed
well like on mobile it just chooses i
think like the first one that you
installed
so if you installed like a like a wallet
for testing like years ago it'll like
open this one when you open the bitcoin
uri
um but and then on desktop it's like
maybe you can configure that somehow i'm
not exactly sure but um like how it's
designed in the operating system
currently it's that the uri is for like
one specific like
uh applications right like facebook or
something facebook has to have their own
uri or whatever it would just be like
opening the facebook app or something it
wasn't like really designed for
like something as opened i've like open
i feel as as as um
as bitcoin
surely that would be solvable using
a simple app that just
knows how to recognize the various bit
21 things and delegate them to like
default like a wallet picker kind of
like that doesn't sound like an app
that's too difficult to develop right
yeah that could be like a like a little
middle ground until the operating system
kind of evolves a bit more um
yeah someone said like the same behavior
as default browser
um
yeah
the thing is it's like uh currently we
use so many
different wallets um
you know i have like i don't know five
ten i'm testing a whole bunch so um
having to set like which one is default
i have no idea which one is default for
me i just like use whichever has like
some fun cinematics and um
uh so i kind of like would like to
switch between them or have the option
to like hey which one do you want to
open
um maybe in the future
i guess that's default bullet and the
right click will open with
yeah to open
yeah
that's uh
yeah but you know like when you check
like like if you click a link on a on on
a website you know then i'll have to
maybe
okay maybe that can actually be
mocked up in javascript or something um
when you right click on a
the
21 uri or lightning uri
it's gonna say uh i'd like in the
context menu
open with oh no i'm not sure
okay
because you need access to the operating
system so
okay maybe not
i think the application switcher route
is probably the easier one to go to
yay guys bitcoin is gonna eat the world
tomorrow
it's
perfect
in two weeks time
oh man well i guess anybody mind a
little bit of a random topic shift
nope
um in terms of plugging other wallets
on top of wasabi instead of integrating
wasabi into other things has anybody
really considered the limitations of the
neutrino filters being tailored just for
bec32
because that would kind of have the
implication of any other type script or
script type
cannot use wasabi as the balance
information back end and would require a
second one to be able to utilize any of
those uh utxos
yep that's an issue
i think that's only really an issue if
you want the network layer
to deliver your block filters um
there's the proposal from
juices
uh
i forget sorry
ravner um the uh
the bip 47 guy
yeah so uh
like
that proposal for
how to do like filtering of uh
transaction data is actually like really
nice it's really flexible um and uh
there's good reasons to to kind of
support that because that would solve
this problem in general um
like that that said
wasabi currently just fetches block
filters from the coordinator so it
doesn't even care about the network that
could get block filters for you know any
type of proprietary uh data so like
filtering by script type by transaction
by like literally anything um could be
defined when when you use it that way
and for what it's worth lucas already
wrote the code for taco filters
okay
well yeah i mean that's that's good if
that's a simple thing and there's
already some groundwork for it but it's
just like that's like absolutely
necessary to be able to just take
general wallets and plug them in here
what about is it possible to
to switch out the entire network layer
with something else like in in the
case of putting wasabi inside b2cp
we have our own tracker right so
we wouldn't need neutrino we have a full
node and we have our own
whole utxo and block retrieval mechanism
that we could use
yeah that would be best
um what
adam can probably say more but i think
currently like the wallet synchronizer
class is responsible for that i don't
know how generic it is but um
like there's
a lot of consideration
uh
under that for like how you fetch
specific data so like does end bitcoin
uh is it also careful to like obtain
blocks from tor nodes or sorry
nodes connected through tor
uh in in uh like and careful not to
um
request
the same like the block data from the
node where you know filter data was
requested from i mean sorry it doesn't
have filter support but like um it's
careful about broadcast and it's careful
about uh block requests is my point
so it's it's it's not it's not on top of
my hand how hard it is how hard this
would be
from an implementation point of view but
but from a theoretical point of view
this doesn't
this doesn't apply to cool node
full nodes right like btc or
spectrum what it's
these concerns are more like light
wallets right
well i mean i think what andrew's kind
of getting at is if you just stuck with
the current like uh
balance retrieval mechanism in wasabi
then that would just eat up a bunch of
resources on the btc pay instance and
like what there's no good reason for
that when it could just hook up more
directly into that and use less
resources
yeah
it also if i'm not mistaken has some
like
uh
smart support for uh pruned nodes right
where you can fetch historical blocks if
you're still missing them
or am i misremembering
uh we talked about that you it was uh i
think we talked about it we suggested it
but
i don't think we added support to fetch
specific blocks but we do have a bunch
of stuff basically so nb explorer is
hooking up to uh to a bitcoin node
uh which can be pruned and then it can
scan stuff through it but it also does a
p2p communication layer so
i think it does
do something that i can't remember
actually if it does
it does a lot of fancy sorry
so sorry wait a moment the point of this
would be to not even build the filters
right
yeah exactly yeah i mean
if there's anything you need to track
mbxplorer can track it in advance with
no issue
yes
no just that if you have your own node
and you trust on your nodes in end
bitcoin there is a pull request that
contains all the messages i mean for
implementing the vip um
157 i think right and all the
communication is is it's okay you can
just fetch the filters from your own
node and you don't need to validate them
right because you know and wasabi will
will find if
if the blocks that it needs
and whatsapp can also be configured to
fetch the blocks from your nodes so
you don't need to build the the filters
and you don't need to do
anything it's it's mostly done
the the
pull request is not merged
because
basically
uh you know the specification says that
you have to first download all the vlog
headers and then once you have that
fetch filter from different sources and
validate them and all that stuff and i i
didn't know how to how the end bitcoin
and i didn't understand how and bitcoin
works in regard of those
things but all the rest is
is
is all done
okay
uh i'm just also curious if we need
to
to handle filters right i mean
you
it
because the way the way in bit and the
explorer is doing it is basically you
tell us track and xbop
um track that tracking address track
whatever and it will as soon as it
detects them
any any transfers to them in any blocks
or the memphis
it will
keep uh um it will take uh
it will download that data and store it
locally permanently it doesn't matter if
the pro note would remove it so
basically we have all the data we need
permanently for these kind of things as
long as we tell it in advance look for
them the abstractions at least in the
v11 release are still pretty leaky like
the wasabi client that synchronizes
the um
the coordinator with the
the app i believe
does require some knowledge about the
filters it doesn't just ask about
transactions i don't know if that
changed to 12 or if i'm looking at the
wrong thing but i think that's how it
works right now because i know the
synchronizer takes care of
getting the
coin joined data as well as the filter
data and i don't know if they're totally
separated
no i mean it's it's not it's not
done because it's not part of our use
use cases but
wasabi works with transactions right
i mean if you connect
wasabi to your now
and you just
or node or software whatever using the
peer-to-peer network and you send
transactions to
wasabi it will processes
and so it doesn't need to to to get
blocks and get filters and get you just
if you know all the your transactions
you can send the transactions to wasabi
and whatsapp will process it and and
and
calculate everything the balance and all
the stuff
and so basically we discover the the we
get the filters to discover the blocks
to get the transactions basically but if
you already have the transactions
and well
of course we need to disable the
synchronizer right because yeah
the synchronizer is the one that tries
to do that that thing
so you just send the transactions to the
to the wasabi mempool and that's all
okay cool yeah that's that would be nice
i think i think it would save a lot of
effort at least on the b2c place at
least memory wise right and
there's no it's already doing all the
hard work underneath no point in
replicating it twice in
the service
cool
yep
uh just curious but what about ending
support for electron servers then
like in
in wasabi directly
well i mean maybe
i think the other way you know i mean
you could expose enemy explorer as um an
electromagnet point and serve like
electrum like just like um electron
personal server or a bitcoin wallet
tracker
uh well yeah my idea is more like if
someone is already running an electrum
server we might as well use that
right like it's about running on the
trusted node and most people who run a
node also have an electron server
so that
and they don't have nba exploit right
only bdc-based service
users use that
so so you're saying wasabi would support
loading plot uh blocks and transactions
through electrum instead of
uh neutrino or
maybe a misunderstood
yeah basically it's an open feature
i think it's a slippery slope to be
honest when you
as soon as you add electron support
people are gonna be like ah i don't need
to run a node
and then they're like just screwing it
up
well you could just set that up
so that it won't call anything but
localhost for that
and
kind of force people to go tweak with
the code
no one will ever go full guys i
promise
i don't believe you
[Laughter]
honestly though i do kind of agree with
andrew that just seems like that would
lead to user stupid
the other direction does kind of make
sense though if you're already using
like nba explorer and you want to use
electrum or a wallet that queries it
like um i think
the
async client uses that
um like it might make sense to
to allow
uh like
serve those requests off of your own
node uh that's already running nba
explorer instead of
yeah i mean we already host software in
uh
in the docker installer for btc pay to
know what it was i think it i think we
have electron personal server
electromax
um
bwt i think is almost there as well so
there's so many options to do it as well
i think nicholas actually wanted to add
like an elect an electrum compatibility
layer but
in the end it was like there's so many
people doing it already
maybe it's not worth it
yeah that makes sense
this is going to be your new mumbles
here for shinobi
never
jitsie will never replace mumble
well but basically you know i was asking
about the compatibility and
interoperability and
ux and uh if i wanted to know if you
know about
if finally page join is something useful
or just uh
i said something like a
developer's brain masturbation or things
like that because it's basically what
she never said
you speak one day with a
bitcoin core developer next day with a
cryptographer then with that
mathematician then we have
office and someone that knows about
nuclear physics and people doesn't know
anything about that in fact there are
people who
who
are victims of
of the most ridiculous scams every day
so people is much much much much stupid
that what you can even imagine and then
the idea that we have to do something
that is really really easy to do really
easy to to to switch from one wallet to
another wallet and privacy has to be by
default in our case because otherwise i
think
it's really hard to
to
to explain people how to use
these
tools
and
well maybe
that
like pay joins specifically
like that can be very useful
if you're doing
a decent amount of volume on chain and
like transacting a lot
um
like
you know the reason i haven't
implemented that for my shirt store is
really two reasons um one i don't wanna
have the on chain wallet with hot keys
um because we're also running a
lightning node but two like
so much more of our payments come in
over lightning
that we're not doing enough volume on
chain to make pay joint make sense you
know what i mean after a couple pay
joins like everything just tied together
in a way that's obviously like this is
all related and there's not enough
separate utxos to kind of isolate and
optimize that so it's like page joint
can be very useful if you're actually
transacting on chain a lot but if you're
barely touching chain
then
you know what i mean
yeah and um you mentioned like
building tools you know people are
stupid those are keywords that i pulled
out there
um
i think the state that we're in right
now you know working on this pay joint
thing or
coin join and all these different
components where
we are building tools and for the mass
market it's uh experiences that we have
to move into right so
like these kinds of like
interactions with pay joints and
figuring that out and creating the
libraries and whatnot it's you know a
lot of it hasn't been done yet um
so it's not a easy drop in that you can
put in any kind of application so that
we can like have really cool ux that
makes sense to the user
um that's familiar with
them uh to them so
we are still at the stage where we're
building out the tools and just as you
said i don't think it's
it's a matter of the users being too
stupid to use them because we are kind
of building tools for ourselves um or
people that are a bit technical so i
think we have to have a bit of empathy
um in that uh the tools that we're
building is not for
um
the mass market you know we need a new
class of software and design for that
well i mean dude this is like this
is just really super long-term stuff in
my mind i mean like transacting is it
needs to lift off chain um which
completely changes the dynamics of
privacy um
like with lightning in a proper state so
that you just have passive privacy for
regular payments and then these types of
coin join mechanics are just going to be
how those things touch chain
but like
you know what i mean like
we're not gonna really be able to put
this kind of stuff in grandma's hands
until
that's the state of things and a lot of
logic can be automated because like
right now on chain like i'm sorry you
can't just automate the logic in a
software wallet like i bought drugs on
the dark net market with this utxo don't
ever tie that to this utxo like
you can't just automate that without
requiring
the user
having to program themselves like all
kinds of complex logic into utxo labels
in a way where the software can reason
about that like you can't like a wallet
can't just look at utxos without the
user programming and defining and
deciding what can tie together and what
can't like how to handle those utxos the
wallet doesn't understand any of that
unless you make it
yeah and as soon as we go to another
application pulling that output
descriptor x ball that we put that in
then all those labels are gone and then
you call the user stupid for um not uh
for for spending that drug tainted utxo
it's like oh well it's your fault and
you should have labeled your utxos it's
like well i did before but
infrastructure didn't allow me to easily
you know migrate to another wallet
i mean this could also go down to
uh
how like a label server right
i think electrum has been doing it for a
few i don't even know if it was an
official electron plugin but there was
an electron label server which allows
you to synchronize labels on utxos and
transactions between
your electron wallets across machines
right
i don't know if that's even still in use
yeah and i would guess it's pretty
similar to what lightning bullets
currently used with encrypted channel
backups and you just encrypt the
this backup information to your
24 words
and
then upload it to whatever server you
want is while it's encrypted
yeah i found what uh shinobi said
earlier today quite funny because um
uh
like uh yeah never copy your private
keys and stuff like that and
you know um
when we do look at like the mainstream
user and stuff uh
how much would like
it's it's a great
ux uh innovation that came out the
mnemonics and stuff
but is that where it ends
um we had wallet data files and you know
um then we had like
if 32 or whatever and then um and then
you know now we have output descriptors
but like is that where it's going to end
um i don't think so and does it also
end with the user
having to like interact with these weird
symbol
pieces of code looking things
i probably not
right
so the way i look at it long term is
your seed
is going to be the bedrock that you use
to encrypt and back up all the stateful
information that you're going to need in
the long term
yep
except the account and the path and all
those other things that you're going to
need so
no no you can still no i think what your
nobody means is that you take all the
metadata that is nonlinear or that is
non-static
or non-deterministic but that is dynamic
like labels like channel backup
transactions and all that stuff
you encrypt that payload with your 24
recovery words
and then you have some ciphertext that
you can upload to arbitrary servers
securely
but you can always recover it if you
have only your 24 words by two you get
even if you have only the 24 words you
get at least your private keys if you
have 24 words and that encrypted payload
you also get all the metadata
well yeah that sounds
that sounds fair um
yeah
by the way um with like previously said
about labels and output descriptors so
um a while ago i was suggesting um this
was before app scripters so
some of the
details were like still
you know kind of open but up script or
solve that but like
if you have a privacy specialized wallet
that's a wallet that in in principle you
could configure any sort of standard or
application wallet
to send all of its change instead of to
its own seed from its own hot wallet
send it to the external like output
descriptor for the privacy wallet and
then a privacy wallet would be in charge
of basically rebalancing everything
uh point pointing making sure there's
separation producing utxos that are then
you know already set up to go back to
the
individual spending wallets that you
need in order to like perform your
various operations in your various
application specific wallets
um so
like
if you structure it this way then
you you're never spending
any coins that have labels associated
with them that's the responsibility of
the privacy wallet to make sure that
like
the hot wallets of the various other
wallets
only have access to coins that they can
spend safely regardless of their um you
know coin selection policy
and if all that from those transactions
always cycles back to the privacy wallet
uh then you can make sure that like
there's no uh like
no no potentiality of um
accidentally uh violating this uh
invariant by spending uh change along
with a different output
or a scenario to change outputs together
so the individual
wallet transactions for you know bisque
or whatever could be completely disjoint
on chain
yeah that's for sure the goal
and that's again why i really like the
idea of having a server-side wasabi
demon running in the background for
always on mixing
and you can just deposit your change
coins or you're receiving clients
directly in there and after anon said it
reached it just gets distributed at a
certain percentage into your cold
storage and spending molds
that's the feature request the size of a
boat oh go shovel
just gonna randomly say that this kind
of different wallet management it just
screams
85.
which one is that
the deterministic seed generation from a
master
seed so like you go down the derivation
path and get a new uh word seed that can
never retrace to the master one
i mean do you really need that level
of
complexity you don't really need that
you can just use different accounts on
on one seed right
the nice thing is have your master cold
storage seed and then generate all the
other seeds for all the other specific
stuff you're using off of that and just
keep that one thing safe to back up them
all
is there anything that implements it
currently just the cold card
but the nice thing is that this composes
with bip 32 like accounts
very cleanly um i mean you can just
configure
uh x pubs or uh you know experts or
use
bip 39
like you just need to keep track of what
you've been doing so that you don't uh
you know you know how it's set up
um but
like
as far as i know like every wallet that
supports bip 39 is a bit 85 compatible
already right
yep you just generate the child word
seed from the master one and just plop
it into something
what if
what if you
if you had to just go with a with the
account routes where you just generate
xbox based on
the scenario you just and you just um
categorize them by like you know you
said the first hundreds xbob accounts
to being you know like low privacy like
instant doxxing
uh level of privacy on those first
hundred accounts anything in the next
two hundred as
um uh
privacy focused and you know so forth
you just categorize it by the hundreds
and then you can just do a spec based on
that like
anything in these levels of accounts
can be kind of safe to use and anything
inside it like if you had to create
categories just based on xbox
you'd have like 100 accounts to use
just with separate wallets kind of
entirely separate wallets
but it's it's not as generally flexible
for users like you know i mean i can
have my cold storage seed make a new one
plug that into wasabi and use that to
make like three more and like i can
always just at any point in that tree
take that key
go easily import that with no headache
or anything into almost any wallet
and that compromises nothing above it in
the tree it's universally compatible i
don't have to worry about nonsense like
a count levels and i can structure that
tree however i want because it's just
toss a seed in something and that can
always just make more seeds
that would make the deplete
a laughing a laughing
situation with it
recovery
why i mean you could just limit yourself
to like
the tree of seeds and only make ten
child seeds or something off of one seed
like so you're just it's a child seed
from one to ten czech stuff
you're expecting the user to do this so
like what if i put put that seed inside
of like another wallet and then that
wallet things it's now the um
the master seed and then i started
driving
um a bunch of different uh new seeds
and
i don't know it
seems difficult how do you keep track of
it i haven't read respect for a bit 85
but
i mean how is it more difficult than
keeping track of accounts and like
assign canonical numbers to it's
literally the same thing as an account
except you get a whole word seed out of
it it's derivation path index number for
that path spit out a new seed yes
the exact same indexing logic um no but
for the new seed that you create you
could then i'm assuming create
additional seeds for that like how do
you stop there
you don't it's an infinite tree exactly
yeah so
it's just a hierarchical deterministic
wallet that has x-pops and experts
but this is just a spec to get each
x-proof into its own unique set of 24
words
that's that's it
so
all it is is just it's easier to import
into stuff
yeah yeah for certain like i like it a
lot i just think the
like and user can get like
really lost because um
yeah maybe they wouldn't export like
import like a
um a grand child of an expert or
something
you know but in the in the case of like
50 micron between something like that
i mean like think about why like you're
you're acting like in the infinity of
indexing space is a problem that exists
for everything in hd wallets everywhere
like why would a user make a great great
great great great great grandchild
instead of just one thing
and a bunch of children
like you know what i mean
like i i don't see the fundamental
difference here in like a user could get
lost in that
yeah i
like again i really like it
because uh one seemed to rule them all
with kind of
fun here
but
um
i think if like if to another wallet
it's just a normal master seed even
though it's a chicken
um
one of the downsides specifically for
privacy is that if the master private
key or even public key gets compromised
it's like the nuclear option where
everything is clustered
and this kind of stands in harsh
contrast to key rotation where you get a
new completely new
wallet that is not linked to the
previous deterministic orbit
yeah but you know ideally you're doing
this off of a cold storage seed that's
never going to touch anything so that's
never going to be compromised so all
you're really worrying about is the
compromise of child
speeds which can't compromise anything
above them
yeah that's true and you wouldn't even
put the master x-pop in any software
wallet i presume you would just always
take the child expo
i imagine the typical use case is
somebody starts using some wallets backs
up seats gets fed up with making more
seed backups
and then says how about i use my brand
new cold card to just make a bunch of
new seats for all of these wallets
to back up one so i think it's not
really
something that like
users that are not already pushing it
are going to even know
exists or care that exists um
and therefore it would be more like uh
you know it's for
managing your your backup policy more
than it is
managing like how applications interact
it's more about like segregating them
whereas like the 32 paths are you know
that's for wallets that need to transact
together on the same
stuff it's just a different use
yeah case get that done
because yeah that would be something
that i would use personally just to
you know not having to generate a whole
bunch of seeds and keep backing them up
all the time and
even confidently i just have to do one
of them
um
it's also nice that i could give these
private keys to my family easily either
or two friends and they think that they
actually have their own wallet in fact
it's all controlled by me
i get all the sets
see like here's a wasabi case like in
terms of bip 85 like you know part of
the or one of the long term goals with
wabi-sabi is to have like slower gradual
rounds and like extend the signing
process so people can just do coin joins
directly out of um
like cold storage
well
um let's say that i want to mix a utxo a
bunch of times and then spit it out into
cold storage um but then maybe
six months later i want to directly pull
that out of cold storage and mix it a
couple more times
like
you can just pop that child seed out of
your hardware device and just make that
your wasabi hot wallet and these two
things directly can interact with each
other you only have that one backup like
you know it that that's the huge win
here like nothing much said it's just
having that singular backup for
something
but you can still have all of these
segregated wallets for different
applications for different purposes
like the nice thing is what we saw we
will work with hardware wallets so you
don't even have to move out of your cold
storage into hot water
what you described there though is like
that's something you can do only once
per child seed though
yeah look but i'm saying like you want
to have like a mix wallet well hey
that's a hot wallet if you want to have
it mixing regularly just let it mix
regularly pop it into cold storage like
you you still have the same backup thing
but both of those things can mix
you know in their own timetables you can
always go remix out of cold storage
you can have that hot wallet that
initially mixes things a bunch of times
but it's all
in the same seat you know like that's
the key point here you get the ability
to have all these different wallets but
your mind is not
exploding over the giant pile of seed
backups you have
why not
your mic is shitty
liar
but you know like why not automate that
in the same way
that you use account to segregate things
just automate using seeds for some
things like if i have my cold storage
and i make my wasabi hot wallet seed all
i'm thinking is that one seed is wasabi
if the wasabi client
breaks that down into a couple child
seeds instead of accounts to segregate
their
that makes zero difference to me in the
back end but if for any reason
like down the line i want to take some
subset of stuff in wasabi and use it
with something else
like bam spit that out word seed
universally like works with everything
but
that that's irrelevant to me unless i
need to do that it's just something
happening under the hood and it's all
nested under a single backup
i guess um what that can because like
the current state is that most
applications use like account zero right
um so
i guess what that can do
is um the change could be going to
like the account zero of that new seed
um
[Music]
uh and then
um in the scenario i think that uh
nothing much was talking about you can
then take that like it's it's it's kind
of separate now from the main seed so
you can
yeah you have a more clear separation of
shinobi was saying between like
the
utx like the change in the
yeah other coins that you have
i don't know if that made any sense but
no i did
for the record this is like
object capabilities uh
you know the way of of doing that uh
like a seed is a capability to generate
like a deterministic wallet and if you
know how to do that uh in a sort of
factory way
um i mean that wallet the master seat is
not going to be discoverable to normal
wallets but
you're basically
like if your privacy wallet is doing
that specifically to avoid accidental
spending that actually kind of makes
sense and then for every individual
subaccount where you you can segregate
funds
you can i mean you have a policy where
like first you can generate it as a hot
wallet and then like all you can really
do is share it with other wallets
but if you generate it externally with a
hardware wallet then it has an
additional phase before it gets exposed
like that uh where it's potentially
usable for cold storage
um and yeah it's uh like having
aspirations
taha lafs kind of works in a similar
like approach where
you i mean it's for storage but like
your
like secret
data
is
basically both the name and the ability
to decrypt something some piece of data
but there are additional attenuated
capabilities underneath that where so
for example you can store to a storage
grid and you can delegate a verification
role where some
somebody can
or i mean you on a backend server like
can run uh something that only knows
how to identify your blocks and um
make sure that
there's like if some
storage servers go down
then like the
data is re-replicated it's it uses like
erasure coding to make sure that there's
enough redundancy
so the verifier
who can like heal the storage on the the
grids like the storage grids don't know
anything about the clients they just
know that they're storing data
the verifier can make sure that the data
is still accessible in case you need to
go online later and the way it's
structured with the
cryptography is
just really nicely models these
different levels of access that you
might want to
allow
for different kinds of users
and
bip 39 seed words are capabilities to
generate a wallet and
about 32 is uh describes a capability
system especially when you use the
hardened generation um
like you can segregate at that level as
well uh like nobody mentioned that yet
but that gives you something
analogous to how um like the 85 can can
segregate different wallets
um because you cannot export an x-bob of
a hardened key um like um
something uh above the that like you you
can't really
um
i mean hashes in order to obtain the the
chain code it hashes the the private key
material that's what a hardened
derivation is
so
like that
uh
that thing is is um
not available to like other
um
like
when you have a different wallet um
it knows nothing about the hierarchy
above it uh whereas if you're using
non-hardened derivation
um like the the linkage between them the
master bip 32 key
and the account key um is uh overt
sorry that was a really roundabout way
of saying that
5.
object capabilities
for realsies though like it's like i i
just
this should
eat
account functions and i don't see why
because it's the same exact abstract
kind of indexing and it's just so much
better portability and segregation
it's like why not all you get is winning
no it's a trade-off
it's a trade-off that's already partly
available with upper descriptors that
was exactly what i was rambling about
now with hardened derivation
like
that that gets you
almost the same segregation semantics as
bip 85 just it requires
wallets to be able to be configured in
that way
only output descriptor wallets can be as
far as i know
uh project idea for anyone out there
listening or anyone in here
uh um
[Music]
uh
like a key
generation like c generation program
where you can set up these
child paths whether it's the
uh
dip 85
or um
or pop out output descriptors just
having like a like you know these like
control panels where you're able to like
change permissions and generate keys and
stuff like that
like generate accounts and manage
accounts
for like some sas products
and having something like that for um to
manage all your bip85 keys
seeds
all right how about some lighter topic
since
cooks you are the
last guest still here
then i'm going to ask you a question
so
what are you thinking about
at
night when you can't sleep
what kind of
problems hits you away
my kind of problems hmm
i don't know i
i'm like
my biggest problem is
how can i convince nikolas to merge my
pull requests
i think that's the closest problem i uh
i think about
have you tried a whip
wrong continent
you can take care of
his child
for a few hours but again wrong
continent
yeah
maybe i can i can hire a nanny
and send it remotely
with like an a special note it's like
merch pull request one five seven seven
or something
although
that might be kind of kidnapping or
something might look kind of weird
or get a long-range drone with a
whipping
okay i i i have to point out nicholas if
you're listening to this at some point
i'm not trying to hurt you that's max
he's trying to condone violence on you
and you should merge my pull requests
we need a mafia
mafia style organization for maintainers
but
on a serious note um
the plug-in system is
almost a result of
me coding a bit too much for btc pay
and about you know
everybody staying sane with
not having to review too much codes
that needs to be you know perfect for
everybody to use in terms of like from
my end i built a lot of experimental
features
that don't necessarily need to be merged
but
something to play with
so the plugin system is kind of
a result of that
thinking it's like i want to build a
small tool that helps somebody with
i don't know exporting their utxos and
uh
importing them into their bitcoin core
wallet or something like that
um
you know it takes a day to do and then a
month to get emerged from
tests reviews by people and all that
stuff so if it's just something i want
to play with
um that's something
something
possible at that point
and also all these integrations as well
like well
i really wanted to do some integration
with wasabi like
over a year ago
maybe even longer but
it's not that easy to do you know it
takes forever to first you have to set
up a docker repo a docker container with
wasabi in it make sure the tests work
around it
apis integration security
so
and obviously we can just embed wasabi
inside btc bay that would be
like directly into the main code because
that would be kind of a leak in terms of
feature scope
scope creep
so
yeah
plug-in system that's
my
biggest mindset right now
that's what i wake up screaming at
myself about
right now
yeah but i have like a thousand and one
feature requests that i want to solve
with plugins
so i'm very happy for them
yeah
but like uh if you if you
if you had to ask path about which
features he wants merged
with regards to the plug-ins it's
the feature of removing features
which is a very valid use case as well
we have so many features in there
like
like all the apps would be so awesome it
could just for example move the point of
sale into a plug-in the crowdfunding
into a plug-in then other people can if
those things are plug-ins that means
people can build similar features as
plugins right so
um what were they asking for like the
other day somebody was asking for a
lottery plugin
before that there was an auction plug-in
all that stuff is kind of similar in
nature
i highly okay i'm i'm gonna get screamed
at by half the people listening to this
probably but i highly highly recommend
you consider um
like
government monopolies and regulations
around um lotteries
[Laughter]
they will get really really really
really pissed if you start taking away
their poor people tax income
well i mean it would be a plug-in right
so the main copies would not have it
somebody has to install it themselves
so technically it's not even part of b2c
paid
maybe
you know maybe some
guy called not cooks comes along and
just creates the plugin and publishes it
right
exactly
we're gonna make so many things obsolete
holy
yeah i think we like to joke as well
that we we're trying to make ourselves
obsolete
it would be pretty nice
that people don't rely on us for
everything so
want to hear a funny story real quick so
i went to the liquor store the other day
and the clerk brought up bitcoin because
i had a bitcoin shirt on and then this
really old dude at the counter playing
the lottery thought that we were talking
about some new lottery game
he's probably the guy asking people to
feature them
isn't that what they said
a lottery where you can only win it's
the best type of lottery
scratch off your uh your 12 words
i had this guy
i had this guy buy me a lottery ticket
once that lost
it was very unpleasant
very unpleasant
the third word matches up
i won
maybe we're all just in a lottery hunt
to get the same wallet as the toshi hat
it's kind of true right i mean
technically we're all trying to get some
wallet that's already has some beauty
excels in it
maybe ought to be ever in your favor
but they're not
they know strong encryption
that would be one of those lotteries
where you won but then lost because
everybody would start panicking and
selling bitcoin
so true
but
like it is possible to generate a seed
that somebody else had
so
if the
like cryptography doesn't change at all
for
some
period of time then
eventually like that would happen right
like probably probably probabilistically
right
yeah unlikely i think actually i think
people i think the sun will burn out
before that
yeah way before
no i don't know too much about that i'm
trusting the cryptographers
so the number of uh
private keys
um
i think that the number of public keys
is um significantly smaller
than the number of possible private keys
uh but both are like on the order of the
number of elementary particles in the
universe and the time to enumerate them
is like on the order of the
black hole epoch or something like that
so like
there's there's not enough universe to
compute a brute force search
on
that kind of thing
unless you have some
like defects in all our random number
generators right
yeah but that that's a an entirely
different thing and and here i mean
there's good reason to believe that we
know how to gather entropy and how to
make it uniform and therefore generate
you know sufficiently close to random
private keys
but that's more or less a solved problem
i mean in the case that it isn't uh
often like those have been stolen anyway
um
like the
brain wallet uh surges uh there's bots
that actively steal any funds are
deposited to like a brain wallet that's
an easy to guess password
oh yeah that happened
10 years ago
that was the
website that would generate the wallets
and stuff and that you'll be able to
like type a
type of like some seed or something
like that
also the blockchain info uh wallet i
think at some point generated uh
duplicate uh seeds
oh yeah the entropy bug
that's that's awesome
holy how can that even happen
um they were calling an external entropy
source if i remember correctly but
didn't include a um error catch for like
error messages so they would be using um
the error message is the entropy i think
but what happened is that work it's way
worse than that they were creating um
random.org for random numbers
oh man
when around
http
when random.org finally made uh htv
forced to redirect to hts
they just
typed the
three direct the 301 or three
four i don't remember redirect into like
that was the entropy
yes that
but that's that's you said that oh she
now he said that that is uh that was uh
just using a random
uh source of entropy
but no no it was usually an external
source like a website external source
random.org that's what it was
yes exactly that's not an external
source of entropy that is a backdoor
right
it's clearly a backdoor
that's so up
it's like you go to a random.org website
some 14 year old kid that coded and
edited in php like 10 years ago most
likely
and returns what like
10 the number 10 or something or what
no you hatch the html that contains the
and then
for what it's worth they also took the
local hardware and the number generator
to get a source of entropy
and then exhort both sources of entropy
uh and that's why random.org was used uh
kind of because it was just another
source of randomness uh to use and
that's just the math benefit
yeah and it actually did help because i
remember correctly the hardware wallet
generator had a bug as well so this one
returned an error code as well and did
not get caught and that bug was even
pre-existing and then for a long time
only random.org was called until that
also shut down so actually the
redundancy prevented the error from
happening
sooner
but because nobody checked the code i
guess it still happened
listen i don't know about you guys but i
only generate my seeds and i'm gonna say
it here
right here live i only generate my seeds
with dice
and um somehow i always roll a six
i don't know but i guess i'm just lucky
i should be down to it but
accident
yeah you should test your dice man
i don't know
maybe i should go to a casino always
rolling
there was a demonstration of some of
those
bad dice
where if you roll them in water they
always roll to the same number
because of the bad weight distribution
on them or something
water and salt
yeah
but you know this is basically like
generating your recovery words is
basically a religious spiritual
experience
uh and you know you can get higher
insights
from the gospels
of the recovery words that are being
laid out at random it's like throwing
bones of rooms
yeah let's go to
the amazon alley and
generator and the entropy
i'm pretty sure random topic change how
has no developer anywhere ever talked
about this delegated signature that
you can do with sig cash none that
jeremy rubin posted to the mailing list
like why the hell has no developer ever
just been like oh hey guys we can do
graft root without craft root
like what what the hell
wait give me a tldr what happened
so you can take my utxoa and your utxob
and i can take both of these
sign them with sig hash nuns so it only
commits to the inputs and no outputs
then you can make whatever the hell
outputs you want sign your signature on
them and i can delegate control of my
coins to you
and i can take it back by spending my
utxo you can relinquish it by spending
your utxo but you can effectively do the
same type of coin delegation that
graphroot allows without craft root
developers have known about this for
years and nobody's talked about
it like you could do so much inheritance
or like you know
escrow type functionality with that it's
it's insane
yeah that's actually true
so you just build a pre-signed
transaction
or does it have to be in this grid
no just sig cash none um
so that my signature commits to your
input and my input but leaves the
outputs for you to define and like
depending on what you do with output um
b you could make that multisig you can
distribute that however you want do some
escrow inheritance however you want
you can time lock the pre-signed
transactions so that you have the window
to back out of it or someone relinquish
it like it's like how the hell
have developers not talked about this
and why is nothing being built with this
like so much inheritance headache
could be solved with this
yeah
well in hindsight it's obvious
how does that work with tampo
um well you could just bury
like whatever conditions under taproot
for your utxob instead of um
like just having them out in the uh the
open or doing a pay to script thing and
revealing all of them later
and you could actually write different
pre-signed transactions
from different tab route spending
conditions
or suspending
branches yep
oh
that can get really complex
oh that's cool
yeah
so like your brother gets this first and
then if something happened to him your
sister can get it and her your mom you
can do whatever the hell you want with
that
and it's all off chain
so what i was saying earlier about like
having
three layers of like wallet
functionality
this is policy right like
i would want my wallets
everything to always have like a taproot
backup condition
that
supports that in principle taproot makes
that economical like you no longer have
to literally put a pdsh uh like redeem
script that can handle that
so like
why wouldn't that be supported in like
composable wallets in the future but
that's an entirely orthogonal layer of
decision making from
what do i want to do with those funds
yep
hey shinobi who who did that jeremy
rubin or robinson
um he was the one who posted it to the
mailing list um jeremy rubin
but it like the way he put it is like
this is something we've known we can do
for forever and i just figured like hey
like
learn about it people
the problem is like
a side can unilaterally like upwards so
it doesn't really give much assurance
but you can play games with that by
making utxo a
multi-sig or more complicated et cetera
et cetera et cetera
yeah tough proof makes it all a lot more
actually useful
but you know i actually kind of like in
in most of the cases i'm thinking about
applying that the fact that a can revoke
it unilaterally at any time and b can
bow out of it unilaterally at any time
you know what i mean
like it you're able to delegate that but
either side is able to like sever that
relationship unilaterally at any time
yep and i mean it makes a whole lot of
sense for uh
like
for example you could imagine
uh a large organization managing um like
a hierarchy of wallet or something like
that so the hot wallets would in the
event of a like a catastrophic loss
um like all of their outputs would
become spendable like a month later by
some master key that's always involved
or policies like that
i'm just struggling to think of other
use cases
well like my head immediately just went
straight to inheritance
like you know people i'm describing is
like basically inheritance just over a
hierarchy right like you can make that
as complex inheritance scheme as you
want and as dynamic as you want
yeah but you know i'm specifically
thinking you know um
like personal inheritance stuff like
that's one one of the biggest problems
in this space is people buying and
holding bitcoin for the long term like
how do i guarantee
that can be recovered in a way that
isn't unilaterally just handing over
control bam right here anyone you want
to be able to claim that you create a
um
a setup like this with whatever utxos
you want them to claim and their key or
utxob and you could even make those
utxops yourself just making dust outputs
because who cares it's just an unlocking
mechanism and then pre-sign that for
however long you want to
like that
can like that just solves that problem
so much and especially the fact that
it's all just pre-signed transaction
based like you can make one of those for
any
um
family member you trust or want to have
involvement or access with that with
appropriate decrementing time locks you
can even make different multi-sig
arrangements between different members
of the family
and it's just like the fact that this
has been possible
pretty much since the beginning of time
um based with what it works on
like that's just crazy to me that nobody
has talked about this and nobody is like
put this to use in those types of
situations like that's the immediate
no-brainer solves a lot of users worries
and problems
yeah seriously like
this enables so many vault constructions
i mean graft route does in general as a
concept but this is basically the
concept of graft food
so this will make the vault construction
so much more easy
like i can almost see in my head now uh
gmax just sitting here obsessing over
this idea and that's slowly evolving
into graft right now
anyway yeah that's what shinobi's been
obsessing about for the last day or so
hey adam if you still want to do an
inheritance software
that just got a lot more easy
a lot more easy
especially if i would have paid
attention
dick
that's why it's live and recorded
it's
it's on the record right it's live
stream so nothing is lost
yep
except my lack of offense
all right guys
then
i'm calling this meeting for myself
if you would like to stay around chit
chat
uh rafa the live stream is on you so
this was uh this was a really
interesting conversation
thank you for everyone for coming bye
bye
what do you mean adam you bow out after
four hours
so quick already
it was a pleasure talking to you again
thanks for coming on
tools
yeah maybe i should
end the live stream already now it's
four hours
or what do you guys think
do we have more interest
how to kill bitcoin
did i say that out loud
yeah okay we have to cut it
but yeah
yeah i'll stop the streaming